<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A spirituall trumpet exciting and preparing to the Christian warfare. Sounded first in the vtmost parts of the Lords campe, to one wing of the armie, now in the midst for the benefit of all. By William Iemmat, Master of Arts, and preacher of Gods word at the Lechlade in Gloucester shire.</title>
            <author>Jemmat, William, 1596?-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 158 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836099</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836099</idno>
            <idno type="VID">346</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04371)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 346)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1353:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A spirituall trumpet exciting and preparing to the Christian warfare. Sounded first in the vtmost parts of the Lords campe, to one wing of the armie, now in the midst for the benefit of all. By William Iemmat, Master of Arts, and preacher of Gods word at the Lechlade in Gloucester shire.</title>
                  <author>Jemmat, William, 1596?-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 284 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. H[aviland] for Iohn Bartlet at the gilt Cup in Cheape-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:346:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:346:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>Spirituall Trumpet:</hi> EXCITING AND preparing to the Chriſtian WARFARE.</p>
            <p>Sounded firſt in the vtmoſt parts of the Lords Campe, to one wing of the Armie, now in the midſt for the benefit of all.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM IEMMAT,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Preacher of Gods word <hi>at</hi> Lechlade <hi>in Glouceſter ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cyp. epiſt. ad Cornel.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Qui in pace militibus ſuis futuram praenunciat pugnam, dabit militantibus in congreſſione victoriam.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. H.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bartlet</hi> at the gilt Cup in Cheape-ſide. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:346:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:346:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To all the LORDS</hi> Captaines and Souldiers, <hi>W. I.</hi> wiſheth courage and victorie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood friends, my purpoſe in publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe few leaues, is, to rub vp the memory of thoſe many good Treatiſes, already extant, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Temptations and the Chriſtian Warfare,
<note place="margin">M. <hi>Taylor,</hi> M. <hi>Downam, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and to bring them into vſe. Pitie it is to ſee,
<pb facs="tcp:346:3"/>how ſo many and ſo good helps are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally neglected; and people for moſt part liue, as if they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of ſpirituall enemies, neither in the Miniſterie, nor other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Certainly it is one maine ſtratageme of our aduerſary, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: <hi>perſwading,</hi> either that there are no ſuch blacke fiends to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or that they haue no power to tempt or corrupt them, through the goodneſſe of their hearts, and the ſtrength of their faith: <hi>and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:346:3"/>them to buſie themſelues about other matters, worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, luſts, vanities, and the treacherie of pretended friends, true enemies. While they run at large in theſe things, they ſhall neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect him, and his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining. Whereto if we adde the ſenſualitie of carnall men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who <hi>cannot</hi> looke vp to things aboue ſenſe, and <hi>will not</hi> when they are called on, wee haue (I thinke) the full cauſe of this vniuerſall ſecuritie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:346:4"/>
            <p>One of theſe rocks is commonly run vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The moſt thinke not on it, whether there be any deuill or no. Many eſpie a deuill, but rather in others than themſelues: And after the ſin is committed, not before: And it muſt be a foule, groſſe, open ſinne too, or elſe it goeth without ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation. The multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is of opinion, that bare ſpetting at the mention of the deuill, and defying of him, is ſufficient: And ſo I haue marked in the
<pb facs="tcp:346:4"/>very treating of theſe things publikely. This is an vnreproueable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and muſt not be called into queſtion. And in other places, where this is laughed at for great ſimplenes (as indeed it is) yet through careleſneſſe, or worldlineſſe, or volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes, or other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe, the deuill keepes vp his ſtrong holds, and ſuffers in no manner as hee ſhould. The ſtory of theſe wars is all they affect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. Yea Gods owne people doe not acqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:346:5"/>themſelus ſo generouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they ought, in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bat; but, by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer euills, take great foiles, and hinder their progreſſe in grace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly. And ſome of them who reſiſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill well and carefully in reſpect of <hi>ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and the exerciſes thereof, yet in reſpect of <hi>conſolation</hi> and thoſe bleſſed priuileges which their heauenly Father allowes them in Chriſt, doe not reſiſt him, but paſſe their daies vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably. But theſe are more to be pitied, than
<pb facs="tcp:346:5"/>blamed: Yet withall muſt bead moniſhed, to reſiſt in this kinde as well as the other: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the deuils malice is ſeene in this, as in that, and God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed victory, as well as enioyned reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>If I may (as a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter) ſtir vp the Lords Campe to conſider bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of theſe enemies, I haue my deſire. For me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the former ſort is the former voice of this Trumpet, in the <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> For thoſe of the latter ſort, the latter voice, in the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:346:6"/>Take both together, &amp; you ſhall acquit your ſelues like men, like men of God.</p>
            <p>Lately I endeuoured by a ſmall watchword to arme Gods people againſt the malignity of the world,
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Matthewes contierſion.</hi>
               </note> which at the worſt, can but put vs to the loſſe of all <hi>worldly</hi> comforts, and muſt ſtill leaue vnto vs God, and Chriſt, and our great Comforter, &amp; our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; integrity of our conſciences, &amp; the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of heauen. And now I attempt the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Arch-ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,
<pb facs="tcp:346:6"/>
               <hi>the god of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4.</note> the prince of darknes. He hath many waies to aſſaile vs, and we haue many weapons to repel him, with promiſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and victory, and a crowne of triumph. There is no one thing that can diſcourage vs, if we be not wanting to our ſelues, in watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in conſcionable vſe of the meanes, and holy endeuours. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs vp and bee doing, and our God will goe out with vs, to aſſiſt vs, and foile our enemies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:346:7"/>
            <p>But I will not pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in the enſuing exhortations Take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (good Reader) as they are; and though they giue not ſo <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>ſhrill</hi> a ſound, as in the hand of the Lords o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trumpeters, yet a <hi>diſtinct</hi> ſound they giue (I truſt) &amp; ſuch as may prepare good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to the battell.</p>
            <p>The Lord of hoſts who hath ordained theſe conflicts, &amp; hath ſaid to his Prophets &amp; their ſucceſſors,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 58.1</note> 
               <hi>Cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud, lift vp thy voice like a Trumpet,</hi> and <hi>Set
<pb facs="tcp:346:7"/>the Trumpet to thy mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.1.</note> vouchſafe a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to theſe my ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, and giue his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a heart to looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, that, while we keepe out <hi>carnall</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, we admit not <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> and loſe not our ſoules by ſecurity while wee preſerue our bodies and outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates by magnanimity. What will it proſit a man to win the whole world, and loſe his owne ſowle? So I reſt, thirſting for a good iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of all theſe trialls and skirmiſhes, to you
<pb facs="tcp:346:8"/>and al the Lords War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, that I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce with you in the day of our full Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lechlade.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uemb.</hi> 27. 1624.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. IEMMAT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:346:8"/>
            <head>A ſhort view of the <hi>Contents of this</hi> Booke.</head>
            <p>THe text con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of a Direction, &amp; Conſolation.</p>
            <p>In the Direction, ſix things are handled.</p>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>The Doctrine propoſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. page 3.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>II.</head>
               <item>The Obiect, or in what the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell muſt be reſiſted.
<list>
                     <item>1. In his own proper ſuggeſtions, mouing
<list>
                           <item>Vnto euill. p. 7.</item>
                           <item>From good. p. 8.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. In the temptations of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments: whereof 3. ſorts. p. 10.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>III.</head>
               <item>The meanes whereby be muſt be reſiſted.
<pb facs="tcp:346:9"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Rules of Preparation: which are three
<list>
                           <item>Sound illumination, in the points. p. 19.</item>
                           <item>Sou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d humiliation p. 26.</item>
                           <item>Sou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reformation. p. 28.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Rules of Oppugnation. Some meanes are Principall: as 1. The Word. 2. Faith. 3. Hope. 4. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. 5. Prayer. p. 30.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Leſſe Principal and auxiliary, as
<list>
                     <item>1. Comfort of conſcience. p. 42.</item>
                     <item>2. Communion of Saints. p. 43.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <item>The manner how the Deuil muſt be reſiſted. Earely: in reſpect of
<list>
                     <item>Our life: three reaſons. p. 46.</item>
                     <item>Any one temptation to ſin. p. 56.</item>
                     <item>Gouragiouſly: wherefoure grounds of courage. p. 60.</item>
                     <item>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally. p. 66.</item>
                     <item>Wifely: where three Rules of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in reſiſtance. p. 68.</item>
                     <item>Conſtantly. p. 75.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>The reaſons why hee muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted.
<list>
                     <item>1. The nature of the reſiſted:
<pb facs="tcp:346:9"/>
                        <list>
                           <item>That euill one: diuers waies. p. 77.</item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <head>Satan: an enemie.</head>
                                 <item>To God. p. 81.</item>
                                 <item>To Chriſt. p. 84.</item>
                                 <item>To the Goſpell. p. 86.</item>
                                 <item>To eminent men. p. 89.</item>
                                 <item>To holy and wholſome orders. p. 90.</item>
                                 <item>To euery particular Chriſtia. p. 93.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <head>The Deuill: accuſing</head>
                                 <item>God to man. p. 95.</item>
                                 <item>Man to God p. 96.</item>
                                 <item>Man to man. p. 98.</item>
                                 <item>Man to himſelfe. p. 100.</item>
                                 <item>Vertues for vices, and vices for vertues. p. 102.</item>
                                 <item>In his inſtruments. p. 103.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The nature of the reſiſter. p. 106.</item>
                     <item>3. The miſchiefes of being foiled, Priuatiue. p. 109.
<list>
                           <item>3. The miſchiefes of being foiled, Poſitiue. p. 111.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <item>The Vſes of the point.
<list>
                     <item>1. To bring out of requeſt the eaſie life of many. p. 112.</item>
                     <item>2. A Caueat againſt ſecuritie and lukewarmeneſſe in the godly. p. 119.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:346:10"/>
                     <item>3. An exbortation to examine our ſelues: where eight markes of right reſiſtance. p. 133.</item>
                     <item>4. A confutation of them who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſuch treatiſes. p. 162.</item>
                     <item>5. Commendation and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them that ſo reſiſt the Deuill. p. 166.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the Conſolation, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Devils flight, are fiue things.</p>
            <list>
               <label>I.</label>
               <item>What it is not. p. 171.</item>
               <label>II.</label>
               <item>What is it.
<list>
                     <item>Partiall and temporarie. p. 174.</item>
                     <item>Totall and finall. p. 176.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>III.</label>
               <item>What leſſon we learne: Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſhill be to them that reſiſt.</item>
               <label>IV.</label>
               <item>What reaſons here are for it.
<list>
                     <item>1. The faithfull promiſe of the mightie God. p. 181.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:346:10"/>
                     <item>2. The valor of our Captaine. 182.</item>
                     <item>3. The validitie of our armour: ſhewed in the parts. p. 184.</item>
                     <item>4. We haue a bruiſed enemie. 189.</item>
                     <item>5. We need ſome refreſhment after skirmiſhes. p. 192.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>V.</label>
               <item>What Vſes are made hereof.
<list>
                     <item>1. Comfort to Gods Warriours: where foure Anſwers to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection concerning the tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this combate. p. 196.</item>
                     <item>2. Fond are they that ſeare perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall moleſtation in Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. p. 204.</item>
                     <item>3. Goe on in reſiſting. p. 208.</item>
                     <item>4. Vſe times of reſpite well. p. 211.</item>
                     <item>5. It is folly to lay all ſlips on the Deuill: for he flies, if he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. p. 214.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the Appendix (out of Gen. 3.15.) gather theſe things.</p>
            <list>
               <label>I.</label>
               <item>Seuen notes of right enmitie againſt the Deuill.
<list>
                     <item>1. If it be of &amp; from God. p. 220.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:346:11"/>
                     <item>2. If it be for God and his glorie. p. 223.</item>
                     <item>3. If we reſiſt him duely. p. 226.</item>
                     <item>4. If we auoid places where hee haunteth. p. 232.</item>
                     <item>5. If wee earneſtly begge of God ſtrength againſt him. p. 236.</item>
                     <item>6. If we be carefull to giue him no aduantage. p. 239.</item>
                     <item>7. If wee zealouſly endeuour to thruſt downe his Kingdome in others. p. 343.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>II.</label>
               <item>Areproofe to three ſorts of men.
<list>
                     <item>1. Of them that thinke not on this enmitie. p. 247.</item>
                     <item>2. Of them that embrace the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie amitie. p. 251.</item>
                     <item>3. Of them that helpe the Deuill in ſtead of hindering him. p. 255.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>III.</label>
               <item>Motiues vnto enmitie againſt the euill ſpirits. Conſider,
<list>
                     <item>1. What they are in reſpect of God. p. 259.</item>
                     <item>2. What they are unto vs. p. 261.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:346:11"/>
                     <item>3. What they are in themſelues. p. 263.</item>
                     <item>4. God hateth them vnreconcila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie. p. 265.</item>
                     <item>5. So alwaies haue Gods faithfull ſeruants. p. 266.</item>
                     <item>6. This enmitie is the ground, or companion of true grace. p. 267.</item>
                     <item>7. There are certaine Meditations to effect this. p. 271.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>IV.</label>
               <item>A teſtimonie of Cyprian, with the Application and Concluſion. p. 275.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:346:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:346:12"/>
            <head>A SPIRITVALL TRVMPET.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IAMES 4.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Reſiſt the deuill, and he will flie from you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thinke it not needfull to looke after any cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene theſe words and the reſt of the context. Our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:346:13"/>purpoſe is to giue good counſell to theſe ſcattered Iewes as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the life and <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of godlineſſe. For the <hi>forme</hi> of it, none more forward than they: and therefore hee preſcribes them ſuch ſubſtantiall duties, as might indeed commend them to God, as the other could not. Among the reſt this is one, <hi>Reſiſt the deuill, and he will flie from you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The parts whereof are two,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Parts</hi> 2.</note> a <hi>Direction,</hi> and a <hi>Conſolation:</hi> or a <hi>Dutie</hi> directed vnto, and the bleſſed <hi>Fruit</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:346:13"/>to them that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Reſiſtance to be made vpon the deuill.</note>From the former we learne, that <hi>it is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gods people to make reſiſtance vpon Satan, till they haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him the foile.</hi> A deuill there is, moſt ſubtill and malicious, who ſeeks by all means poſſible, to rob vs of the inheritance of the Saints in light, and make vs miſerable like himſelfe: and our care muſt be, to oppoſe, to reſiſt, to diſappoint him. With <hi>S. Iames</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords <hi>S. Paul, Eph.</hi> 4.27
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:346:14"/>
               <hi>Giue no place to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill:</hi> yeeld not an inch. And with them both agreeth <hi>S. Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>epiſt.</hi> 5, 8, 9. <hi>Your aduerſarie the deuill. Whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> he ſtands againſt you, therefore doe you withſtand him: he will bee ſure to giue no ground, till he needs muſt, therefore turne not your backs vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, ſtand your ground.</p>
            <p>Here foure materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all queſtions come to be anſwered,
<note place="margin">Foure queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons propoſed.</note> the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution whereof will
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:346:14"/>giue great light to the Chriſtian Combatant.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>I</label> 
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Wherein ſhould we reſiſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="I" place="margin">I. Reſiſt him in his owne perſon.</note>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In two things.
 Firſt, <hi>in his owne proper ſuggeſtions.</hi> He makes not daintie of doing his worke, yea in his owne perſon, though the Defendant be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo meane and baſe in the world. None ſo good, but he hopes to make him bad: None ſo bad, but he hopes to make him worſe, or at leaſt to keepe him as bad as he is: therefore
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:346:15"/>he refuſeth not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent himſelfe to any, but in a diuers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; ſometimes viſibly, ſometimes and more commonly, inuiſibly; ſometimes pleaſingly, ſometimes terribly; ſometimes by outward obiects, ſometimes by inward motions, and that more ordinarily. Being a ſpirituall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he eaſily applieth himſelfe to our ſpirits, our fancies and minds: and, vnleſſe he be well watched and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, he makes great battery vpon the ſoule,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:346:15"/>darkens the iudgment, benummes the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, perſwades the will, and diſtempers all the affections: and then doth his beſt to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inue this diſorder.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Motions to euill. <hi>Vnde venis? ab homicidijs, à ſanguinib. ab a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterijs, &amp;c. Orig. in Iob</hi> 1.7</note>As for example:
 The deuill put into <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> his heart to betray Chriſt, and preuailed. Hee put into <hi>Dauids</hi> heart to number the people, and preuailed. He put into <hi>Eues</hi> heart to ſwallow the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit, and her owne bane, and preuailed likewiſe. So at this day, by the inſtinct of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:346:16"/>deuill it is, that men are carried along to pride, to couetouſneſſe, to vncleanneſſe, and the moſt loathſome cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<note place="margin">Matth. 8.32.</note> as the <hi>ſwine</hi> into the lake. In this reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Diſſwaſions from good: as 1. from zeale.</note>Reſiſt him alſo in motions to lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
 or apoſtaſie. A chiefe part of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment is, to hinder good, that either it may not be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or not continued. It is he that diſſwades men from care in the purſuit of religion; What need they be ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:346:16"/>hot? and what encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement doth the world giue them for ſuch peeuiſh courſes? <hi>Maſter, ſpare thy ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Matth. 16.22.</note> it ſhall not be ſo vnto thee,</hi> thou needeſt not be at ſo much charges in the matter of pietie. Here is a dart of the deuill, here reſiſt him, and ſay as Chriſt to <hi>Peter,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 23.</note> Get thee behinde me, Satan, for thou art an offence vnto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many a man he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades,
<note place="margin">2. From con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie.</note> not to hold out in his religious begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, ſhewes him the courſe of the world,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:346:17"/>the backe-ſlidings of ſome, the harſhneſſe of his courſes, and the pleaſures or profits that he might haue; and,
<note place="margin">Iob 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Doeſt thou ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thine innocencie? blaſpheme God, and die;</hi> forſweare thy profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all; take thy ſwindge, and pleaſe thy ſelfe, thou wilt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be younger. This is the blacke voice of a blacke ſpirit. Herein reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">II. In his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments.</note>Secondly,
 reſiſt him <hi>in the temptations of his inſtruments.</hi> That hee may leaue no ſtone vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:346:17"/>to aduantage himſelfe, or diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage man, he furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth men with varietie of euill arts, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them his factors, to deale for him in all places. For what? Though ſimple people take the deuill for their enemie, yet can they thinke ſo of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? will their owne fleſh and bloud de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them? Yes: he hath many Agents whom hee ſets on worke to deceiue the world,
<note place="margin">Three ſorts of factors for the deuill.</note> and loſeth not his labour.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:346:18"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt,
falſe prophets, or erroneous teachers, who corrupt the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; as in Poperie, Browniſme, Arminia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, and other ſects, which creep in among Gods people by the flie inſinuation of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly,
libertine teachers, who infect the life by handling the word of God looſely and deceitfully; as in profanation of the Sabbath, formalitie of worſhipping God, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp;c. In all which,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:346:18"/>they nothing elſe but doe that openly, which Satan doth ſecretly: and therefore they are called <hi>his Miniſters,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.15.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly,
thoſe that are either ſcoffers, or hinderers, or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the truth. Some can only barke againſt the Sunne, and doe no harme; as thoſe that put nicknames, and reſts, and flouts vpon Profeſſors. Others haue authoritie alſo, as ouer children, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; and theſe can diſhearten them by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:346:19"/>frownes, and checks, and vile vſage, to make them weary of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Others haue fire and faggot to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and any extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities they pleaſe; and theſe can violently make away the godly, till the houre of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be ouerpaſt.</p>
            <p>Al theſe <hi>receiue their power from the dragon, Reu.</hi> 13.4. and come with his commiſſion, as Chriſt intimates, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.30. <hi>The Prince of this world commeth:</hi> that is, in <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor, in the Iewes my
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:346:19"/>accuſers, in the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers my executioners, in the people that wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged their heads, railed on me, mocked mee, bid mee come downe from the croſſe, and ſaue my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee, how Satan laieth about him both by himſelfe, and by his inſtruments, to put vs to the worſe. In both theſe, ſuggeſtions inward, and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons outward, we muſt make reſiſtance vpon him. And this of the firſt queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. With what<pb n="16" facs="tcp:346:20"/>ſhould we reſiſt him? for of our ſelues we are bare, and naked, and vnable to encounter him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Inſufficient weapons for this warfare, three kindes.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>  Aske coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers &amp; charmers, they will tell you, you muſt make circles,
vſe ſpels, amulets, and I know not what.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Aske ſimple people,
and they will tell you, you muſt ſpet at the mention of him, bleſſe your ſelues from him, defie him heartily, and all his workes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Aske Popiſh Prieſts,
and they will tell you,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:346:20"/>you muſt ſprinkle your ſelues with holy water, carry a Crucifix about you, and croſſe your ſelues well at your mouth, forehead, eyes, eares, breaſt, and other parts. Theſe are the ſtrawes which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill hath taught men to fight withall, and in the meane time laughs at them in his ſleeue:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exire ſe ſaepe dicit, &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l. t. epiſt. ad Magnum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>often pretending</hi> (as <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> obſerued in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſts) <hi>to goe forth, and leaue the ſeruant of God, but deceiuing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But aske counſell at the wiſdome of God,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:346:21"/>and we ſhall finde ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of proofe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. The word tels of <hi>ſpirituall ſcourges</hi> (as the ſame Father elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where calles them) wherewith the deuils are tortured;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Torquentur ſpiritalibus fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris, &amp; pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate diuiua: lib. ad Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trianum.</hi>
               </note> and of <hi>the power of God,</hi> whereby only they can be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The weapons that are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, in two heads.</note>The meanes then of reſiſtance ſtand in two ſorts of Rules:
 1. Of <hi>Preparation,</hi> 2. Of <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnation.</hi> With ſome things the Chriſtian muſt be furniſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, and ſome other things hee muſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:346:21"/>vſe in the skirmiſh it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The firſt in three things:
<note place="margin">1. Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue.</note> 1. Sound illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,
<note place="margin">3. In ſpeciall.</note> or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. 2. Sound humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, or repentance. 3. Sound reformation, or holy life. Neuer goe into the field without theſe: for theſe are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and they put metall into a man, as one that may be bold.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Knowledge. of 3. points.</note>Firſt,
 the ſpirituall warrior muſt be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to get ſound illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, that he may know why, &amp; in what he muſt reſiſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:346:22"/>he muſt labour to ſee,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt, Gods inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ordaining theſe conflicts; <hi>Ges.</hi> 3.15. <hi>I haue put enmitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thy ſeed and her ſeed; he ſhall breake thine head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</hi> Conſider, the battell is Gods, the quarrell is Gods, the armour Gods, the ſtrength Gods, and the valour and victorie are Gods alone. And ſay as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.45.</note> I come to thee in the name of the Lord:</hi> I come not vnſent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe, commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:346:22"/>or authoritie: no, the God of heauen preaſt me into the field, he gaue me my preſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money, and liuerie, and bade me fight, and ſo I will.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi>
               </note> God makes peace for vs with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Ieſus Chriſt; with the creatures, by vertue of that coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the operation of the Holy Ghoſt: but no peace with Satan; his ſin is vnpardonable, therefore himſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnpeaceable, vnreconcilable. Know this.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:346:23"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly,
know the prouiſion &amp; furniture of the deuill. Be fully acquainted with his malice, and ſubtiltie, and vnweariableneſſe: how he is expert in his forces, and diligent in muſtering and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to the very end of thy life. Be able to ſay as the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. <hi>We are not ignorant of his deuices.</hi> How ſhall a Captaine be able to enter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with the enemie, if he know not his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, plots, ſtratagems, ambuſhments? <hi>What
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:346:23"/>King goeth to warre,
<note place="margin">Luk. 14.31.</note> and ſitteth not downe firſt, and taketh counſell, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be able with ten thouſand to meet him that commeth against him with twentie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand?</hi> Should he goe forth a little way, and then flie, or ſend for conditions of peace? Here therefore know, that the deuill is an old ſerpent, the wiſeſt of all beaſts, a beaſt of ſeuen heads, and euery head hath many turnings and windings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doe thy beſt to take an <hi>anatomie</hi> of them. Reade the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:346:24"/>works of thoſe godly men, who haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Chriſts Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations: Eſpecially learne what it is wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thy ſelfe art moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted; and know theſe things more by practiſe, than by hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> know thine owne impotencie and inſufficiencie for ſo great a combat, both in skill and power. He that knowes himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e aright, cannot preſume (as ſimple ones doe) that he can keepe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe well enough; or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:346:24"/>as the ſonnes of <hi>Sceua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19.14.</note> who would needs fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret the fox out of his owne hole, to their owne ſhame &amp; harme: But he will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his vnskilfulneſſe and faint-heartedneſſe, and ſay to himſelfe as <hi>Saul</hi> ſometime ſaid to <hi>Dauid,</hi> Alas, <hi>thou art a childe,</hi> thou art not able to fight with this man of warre, this <hi>Goliah</hi> of hell, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.33. He will flie out of himſelfe for ſtrength, betake him to the banner of Chriſt, and looke for the accompliſhment of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:346:25"/>the viſion ſhewed to <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pol. Virgil.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is (in the language of Scripture) to bee a <hi>conquerour, and more than a conquerour, through him that loued him, Rom.</hi> 8.37.</p>
            <p>This as concerning illumination.</p>
            <p>Next,
<note place="margin">2. Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> the ſpirituall warriour muſt looke carefully to ſound hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation. If hee will looke his enemie in the face, and fight the field manfully, he muſt firſt make all ſure at home, and ſee, that there be no home-bred ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:346:25"/>and lurking trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors within his owne walls. See <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7.10.11, 12. Euery ſinne is an aduerſarie to thy ſoule, yea a tyrant, and muſt not be ſuffered to reigne in thy mortall body, leſt it ſet God at ods with thee. If there were no deuill in hell, yet ſomething in thy ſelfe is ſufficient to foile thee. Sinne is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely euill, as Satan is not. Therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rooſt this curſed brood, humble thy ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, put away the accurſed thing: ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:346:26"/>ſhalt thou be able to ſtand, where otherwiſe thou muſt needs fall. It is our Apoſtles me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in this place; firſt, <hi>ſubmit your ſelues to the Lord;</hi> then, <hi>reſiſt the deuill:</hi> and verſe 10. <hi>Humble your ſelues in the ſight of the Lord, and he ſhall lift you vp;</hi> higher than Satan can reach you, or pull you downe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Holineſſe and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of life.</note>Further, the ſpirituall warriour muſt haue a ſpeciall care of ſound reformation, or holy conuerſation. For this is that which Satan
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:346:26"/>moſt laboureth againſt, either to preuent it, or interrupt it; and that which moſt confounds him in his enterpriſes: therefore it is called <hi>the breaſt-plate of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, Epheſ.</hi> 6.14. becauſe it keepes off gun-ſhot, darts, ſpears, and all the deuils mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition. As <hi>Iob,</hi> by ſound holineſſe in his heart and life, ſwome thorow a great ſtreame of violent oppoſitions. <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.1. <hi>The righteous is as bold as a Lion:</hi> and ſo euery good man ſindes, that vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:346:27"/>is a great prop to boldneſſe and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">II. Oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue.</note>Now to the Rules of Oppugnation: that is, ſuch as whereby he may either ſet vpon Satan, or keepe him off from giuing him the ſtab. A Chriſtian pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and furniſhed as before, muſt ſee, that he take vnto him <hi>the whole armour of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.13.</note> and vſe it, and ſtill keepe it about him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In 5. ſeuerall peeces.</note>The ſeuerall peeces hereof are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>the word of God</hi> is the ſword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:346:27"/>
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. able to cut off Satans temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and preſerue our graces. Chriſt ſtill reſiſted him with this, <hi>It is written;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 4. Luk. 4.</note> which put him ſo to a <hi>Non-plus,</hi> that he was not able to replie vpon him in the ſame kinde. This ſhewes vs the validitie of the word: It is <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to exhort, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, to conuince, and inſtruct in righteouſnes,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. No error in doctrine or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by it: no truth, no holy duty but is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:346:28"/>and continued, and perfected by it: Therefore buckle this ſword of the Spirit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hide the word in thy heart, that thou maiſt not ſinne against God.</hi> Oppoſe Scripture to all temptations; as of earthlineſſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Seeke the things which are aboue: ſet your affections on things aboue, and not on things vpon earth.</hi> Of pride and vaine-glory, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Let nothing be done through ſtrife or vaine-glory, but in low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of minde let each
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:346:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>eſteeme other better than themſelues.</hi> Of looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; timorouſneſſe in matter of religion, <hi>Reu.</hi> 3.19. Repent, and <hi>be Zealous:</hi> and if any tell you this is peeuiſh, or the like, tell them againe, No, it is <hi>good to be alwayes Zealouſly affected in a good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Gal.</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>faith in the Sonne of God</hi> is a ſpeciall weapon for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the deuill: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8, 9. <hi>Whom reſist, ſtedfaſt in the faith;</hi> firmly aſſenting to the whole truth, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:346:29"/>of the Goſpell, with application of it to ones ſelfe for iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and direction, and ſaluation. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Aboue all, take the ſhield of faith, wherewith yee ſhall be able to quench all the fierie darts of the wicked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Faith, how it is ſo helpfull in this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</note> And thus faith can helpe vs, partly for that it lateth hold vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt, who hath broken the Serpents head, and put away the enmitie, and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Father to vs: (ſo it can well ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and Satan; for,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33, 34.</note> 
               <hi>how can hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:346:29"/>when God iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth?</hi>) and partly, in that it drawes vertue from Chriſt, both in the example of his life, and by the power of his death and reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to ouercome as he hath ouercome: He is the Head, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence quickneth the whole Chriſtian, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirre himſelfe as the member of ſuch a powerfull Head.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly,
another peece of our ſpirituall armour is <hi>hope,</hi> to wit, an aſſured expectation of the mercy of God,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:346:30"/>that he will ſurely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide meanes for vs to hold out in grace vnto glory. This is called the helmet of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.8. And why a helmet? Becauſe when Satan raineth downe his ſnares as thicke as haile (from the high places where he hath his abode, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12.) and vexeth the Chriſtian with threats of hell and damnation, then hope lifteth the heart vpward, to a power that is higher than he, who hath ſaid, <hi>I will not leaue thee,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> nor
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:346:30"/>forſake thee.</hi> It lookes to God aboue hope, and againſt hope; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Surely he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, though I be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull: He hath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me effectually, and though I of my ſelfe be not able to doe his will, yet <hi>he will doe it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.24.</note> He hath begun a good worke in me, and will ſurely finiſh it: As for thee, Satan, thou art a lier, I beleeue thee not; I will vſe the meanes of perſeuerance conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, and then a but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton for thee; thou art a dogge in a chaine,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:346:31"/>wounded with a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wound, and the God of peace will <hi>tread thee ſhortly vnder my feet, Rom.</hi> 16.20.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>Patience</hi> is a ſpeciall part of the Chriſtians Armour: Hereby he ſhal be able to <hi>poſſeſſe his ſoule,</hi> which otherwiſe will be loft through fretful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and impatience, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.19. Satan is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant in his malice, to wearie vs out by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie. Hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes too often in his enterpriſes, to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing of our peace
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:346:31"/>and confidence: and hangs diuers clogs at our heeles, to keepe vs from fighting; as namely, the frownes of acquaintance, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturalneſſe of friends, the reuilings of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, &amp; the violence of ſecular authoritie; that, if one cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten vs, another may, or all put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may not faile. So that we <hi>haue need of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.36.</note> that wee may receiue the promiſes.</hi> Therefore while wee walke among theſe ſnares, and thornes,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:346:32"/>and rubs in our way, we muſt get our <hi>feet ſhod with the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpell of peace, Eph.</hi> 6.15.</p>
            <p>Fiftly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>Prayer</hi> is the bond that ties all the other peeces together: as there, verſe 18. <hi>Praying alwayes with all praier and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Spirit, and watching therunto with all perſeuerance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praier how it is helpfull.</note> Pray, to eſpie a temptation when it commeth: pray, to bee able to vſe the armour which God hath put vpon vs, to be reſolute and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:346:32"/>for the truth, to be deliuered from euill, that wee may not enter into temptation, or be left to our ſelues and Satans courteſie: And when the battell goeth ſore againſt vs, crie aloud (as <hi>Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> in the armie) for aid and ſuccour from God, and ſay, Lord rebuke Satan, magnifie thy power in confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mee, and giue me grace to reſiſt vnto bloud.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the maine weapons for reſiſting
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:346:33"/>
               <note place="margin">Two ſubſidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie aids.</note>the deuill:
 For the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter managing whereof, vſe theſe two helps.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, keepe thy ſelfe in ſuch a temper, that thou maiſt alway en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the benefit of a <hi>good and a pure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> Dubbe it not with the filthineſſe of any ſinne: let none be admitted willingly, or wittingly, nor conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vnrepented of: for this would choake thy conſcience, when it ſhould haue a voice to checke thee. Yea la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour on the contrary, to fortifie and cheare it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:346:33"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hic murus ahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus eſto, Nil conſcire ſibi, nulla palleſcere culpa.</hi>
               </note>vp with the ſweet teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of vprightneſſe and integritie: So ſhall it be bold to ſpeake for thee, and anſwer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. Marke alſo the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and checks, and recoilings of it: and make a good vſe of them; becauſe this tends to the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the former weapons.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> bee ſure thou <hi>liueſt indeed in the Communion of Saints.</hi> As thou beleeueſt it, ſo make vſe of it; which is, by ioyning thy forces with the reſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:346:34"/>of Gods people. Pray for the brethren who endure the ſame skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes abroad in the world: help them with thy counſell, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences: and be as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die alſo to take profit from them: ſuffer the word of admonition, yea craue it, depend vpon their lips that they may feed thee: deſcrie what policies of Satan thou haſt met withall, and wherein he is moſt happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed: Compare tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and conqueſts, and counſels: Ioyne all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:346:34"/>and you ſhall all ſpeed the better: So did the Apoſtles and Diſciples againſt the rage of the deuill in his inſtruments, the chiefe Prieſts and their whole Councell, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.23-31.</p>
            <p>And this be ſpoken of the ſecond queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. In what manner ſhould we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the deuill? or what are the conditions of ſound reſiſtance?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Reſiſt the deuill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, reſiſt him <hi>earely and timely;</hi> and that, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thy life, and in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:346:35"/>reſpect of any one ſin, whereby hee would haue euill done, or good left vndone.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of thy life, 3. reaſ.</note>For the former: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin thy life with this holy combat, and end it in the ſame. Thy whole being on the face of the earth, from thy birth-day to thy dying-day, is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall warfare. Thou art borne in a campe, among ſouldiers and armour: Thy Parents by their profeſſion are of the traine band, fighting vnder the conduct and colours
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:346:35"/>of the Lord Ieſus: And canſt thou expect im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie? expect it not: no part of thy life is free from hazzards; therefore let none be free from watchfulnes, from reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>And the equity here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſtands vpon three other reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, remember there is an old grudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thee and Satan in this very reſpect. He was enuious &amp; ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at the proſperitie of mankinde, as ſoone as it began: could not endure to ſee man ſo
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:346:36"/>happy, and himſelfe ſo miſerable: laid about him, how to ſtrip our fathers and vs of all thoſe robes of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherewith God had cloathed vs, and leaue vs naked to his owne condemnation: and hee neuer ceaſed till he had effected his purpoſe. And is not this a good argument, to reſiſt him timely? What braue or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpirit can put vp ſuch an iniurie? What? no reuenge for ſo great an indignitie? <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note>Shall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan bee <hi>a man ſlayer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:346:36"/>from the beginning,</hi>
 and wilt not thou be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill-ſlaier (at leaſt a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſter of the deuill) from thy beginning? Did hee owe thee a ſpight, when thou hadſt done him no wrong, and doeſt thou owe him no ill-will, ſince he hath done thee the greateſt wrong that can be? Conſider his forwardneſſe to vndoe thee, and be thou as forward to oppoſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, conſider this, that God hath ſcarce euer raiſed vp
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:346:37"/>any notable inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to repaire his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caied Church, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat Satan of his mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſes, but he hath preſently beſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and hinder it, and make it forceleſſe. <hi>Abel</hi> was a moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and holy man, very hopefull, and likely to eſtabliſh the pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie and poſteritie, if he had liued: therefore what ſhould the deuill but cut him off quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſhed his bloud by his owne brother?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:346:37"/>
               <hi>Iehoſua</hi> was willing and ready to doe much good for the Temple of the Lord at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> therefore what ſhould Satan but <hi>ſtand at his right hand and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him? Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 3.1.</note> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vpon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion ſet himſelfe to preach the Goſpell, and plant Churches among the nations: therefore what ſhould Satan but ſet himſelfe to ſtirre vp tumults, and doe his beſt euery way to <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him?</hi> The Church,
<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.18.</note> the Spouſe of Chriſt, is <hi>a woman, Reuel.</hi> 12.1.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:346:38"/>
               <hi>cloathed with the Sun,</hi> that is, in the robes of Chriſt <hi>the Sun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> and the <hi>moone vnder her feet,</hi> that is, diſeſteeming and trampling vpon all theſe vaine and tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie things in the world: and <hi>hath vpon her head a crowne of twelue ſtarres,</hi> that is, profeſſeth the doctrine of the twelue Apoſtles, which ſhee accounts her crowne and glory. This woman, being married to Chriſt, is often <hi>with childe</hi> by her husband, to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:346:38"/>of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe. Now marke the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Prince of darkneſſe in this caſe, verſ. 4. He ſtill plaieth <hi>rex</hi> in the Church, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe <hi>a third part of the ſtarres</hi> from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to earth, that is, many Preachers and Profeſſors of the truth, partly by erroneous doctrine, and partly by a prophane courſe of life. But eſpecially if there be a childe to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orne, who ſhall <hi>rule all nations with a rod of iron,</hi> that is, mightily
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:346:39"/>ſubiect them to the obedience of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell; if ſo, now hee vſeth more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary diligence to ſpoile the birth, and deuoure the childe: ſo ſaith the Spirit, <hi>The dragon ſtood before the woman which was ready to be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to deuoure her child as ſoone as it was borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neuer doth there peepe a ſpeciall beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full plant in the garden of God, but inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently hee doth what he can to crop it away. Therefore ſee herein his malice, and learne
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:346:39"/>by himſelfe to reſiſt him early. Shall he be watchfull for euill, and we not watchfull for good, or to preuent euill?</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> remember thou madeſt a vow at the beginning of thy life in baptiſme, that thou wouldeſt bee a faithfull ſouldier for Chriſt, from that time forward, euen to thy liues end. Euer ſince thou waſt baptized, thou waſt bound by thine owne ſolemne promiſe, to this reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt Satan:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:346:40"/>Therefore looke to it. Where is the word of an honeſt man? where the word of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an? If thou haſt not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto reſiſted the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, begin now, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlow no more time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. In the firſt propoſall of any tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Centere caput ſerpentis, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>caue primam peccati inſinuationem, Cornelia Lapide in Geneſ.</hi> 3.</note>Againe,
 reſiſt him early (as in reſpect of <hi>thy life,</hi> ſo) in reſpect of <hi>any ſinfull motion</hi> put into thy minde, whether to call thee from good, or egge thee on to euill. Theſe are matters that need no deliberation, and to conſult with fleſh and bloud in theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:346:40"/>is moſt dangerous. What ſhould fire doe neere to gunpowder, or flax? Yet ſuch is our corrupt nature to the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan: eaſily conceiues miſchiefe, and brings forth confuſion. And what ſhould Satan, that ſubtill fox, be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to ſet foot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the doores of the houſe of our ſoule? wil he not ſoone winde in his whole body?</p>
            <p>If <hi>Eue</hi> will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to enter parly with the ſerpent, and make a demurre concerning
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:346:41"/>the commandement, will hee not ſoone worke her to pride, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie, rebellion, and apoſtaſie? Therefore it will be good for the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 39.</note> to doe as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did toward his laſciuious Miſtreſſe. Being ſollicited to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, hee neuer fumbles for the matter, neuer ſaith, I pray giue mee time and leiſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, yet I cannot, but I may hereafter: no, but he giueth her a plaine deniall at firſt,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 8, 9.</note> God forbid that I ſhould doe this thing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:346:41"/>and ſinne againſt God, againſt my maſter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee his wife, my owne ſelfe, and the holy couenant of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stultis vaniſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> promiſſionibus nullus à corde Chriſtiano dari debet acceſſus, ſed primis util<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation bus obui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are debet ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens manu. Cyp. de ieiumo &amp; tentat.</hi>
               </note>Hee that meanes to foile ſpirituall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
 muſt giue the onſet betimes. He muſt not ſtraine his wits, and trie whether hee can ſtretch his conſcience to ſwallow ſome ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie or other, and then deuiſe ſome ſhift or excuſe to couer the filthineſſe, but giue it a cleare repulſe at the firſt propoſall.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:346:42"/>
            <p>And this is the firſt condition of right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the deuill.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">II. Reſiſt the deuill coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly.</note>Secondly, reſiſt him <hi>couragiouſly.</hi> Here we ſay to Gods people, as <hi>Iahaziel</hi> the Leuite ſometimes ſaid to <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat,</hi> and the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> going to fight againſt a great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Moabites and Ammonites, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.15. <hi>Feare you not, neither be afraid for this great multitude; for the battell is not yours, but Gods:</hi> Feare not the whole legions of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh infernall ſpirits,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:346:42"/>nor faint becauſe of their forces; for if you knew all, you would ſee you haue ſmall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be afraid. In the warres of men, there are many things that put courage into a man; as for example, goodneſſe of the cauſe, valour of the Captain, truſtineſſe of the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſouldiers, and weakneſſe of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. All this, and more than this, may be ſeene in this conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. grounds of courage in this fight.</note>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>whoſe is the battell?</hi> not ours, but Gods: therefore moſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:346:43"/>iuſt, moſt holy, moſt equall and reaſonable. It is only to preſerue his glory to him alone, by the killing of ſinne, and the maintaining of his owne Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and conſequently to deliuer poore cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſoules from hell and damnation. And why ſhould Satan rob God of his honour, and his people of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? Who would not be manfull in ſuch a quarrell?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly,
<hi>who is our Captaine?</hi> is it not the Lion of the tribe of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah?</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:346:43"/>is it not he, who ouerthrew the deuill alone in a ſingle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat? Hee,
<note place="margin">Reu. 12.7, 8.</note> who thruſt downe the dragon and his angels, that their place was no more in heauen? He, who hath him in chaines, and confines him when he liſt, to the bottomleſſe pit? Who would not doe his beſt ſeruice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a victorious leader?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>who are our fellow-ſouldiers?</hi> are they not the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, who are bold as lions? are they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:346:44"/>ſuch as will <hi>reſiſt vnto bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.4.</note> and neuer giue ouer till the field bee won? Are not the holy <hi>Angels</hi> on our ſide,
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> who are the fierie cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and glorious ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord of hoſts? and doe not all the godly, in all parts of the world, cloſely follow the ſame cauſe? Who would not bee couragious, when hee ſtands with ſuch cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly,
<hi>who are our enemies?</hi> are they not the enemies of God and al godlineſſe?
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:346:44"/>tortured with the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of an accuſing conſcience, and partly with the torments of hell? Are they not of a crauenly brood, which will ſhe if they be reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted? Who would not ſtand out the brunt of the battell, when hee knowes his enemies ſhall run away?</p>
            <p>Thinke on theſe things, and be not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended either with the multitude, or the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or the violence, or the importunitie of Satans temptations, therfore to flinch back,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:346:45"/>and ceaſe fighting. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it is his nature to doe his beſt againſt thee, by doing the worſt, in the worſt manner that may be; and when he hath ſpent his powder, he muſt be gone.</p>
            <p>This is the ſecond condition: Be coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">III. Reſiſt him vniuerſally.</note>Thirdly, reſiſt the deuill <hi>vniuerſally,</hi> in all his feats and arts of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing. Quench <hi>all</hi> the fierie darts of the wicked, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. One poiſoned dart is enough to kill thee,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:346:45"/>one luſt to condemne thee. Satan is like that Champion who ſaid, <hi>Let me ſmite him once,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.8.</note> I will not ſmite him the ſecond time.</hi> Keepe but one ſinne, which either the Miniſterie, or thy conſcience checketh, and Satan deſires no more; that one is too much. What auailes, whether a man die of the peſtilence, or of the famine? by a ſword, or by a bullet? if he die, it is all one to him. Therefore giue <hi>no place</hi> to the deuill: labour to be as Chriſt, who was
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:346:46"/>good enough for him at euery turne; the Prince of the world came, and found <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> in him; he out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood all Satans malice, and fruſtrated all his policie, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.13. <hi>When he had ended all the tentation, he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him for a ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">IV. Reſiſt him wiſely.</note>Fourthly, reſiſt the deuill <hi>wiſely:</hi> March craft with ſubtiltie, and oppoſe ſerpentine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the wiſdome of the ſerpent. A man that hath a wilie and politicke fellow to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:346:46"/>deale withall, had need ſummon his wits toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and doe his beſt to defeat his counſels: So in this caſe, the Chriſtian who hath to doe with Satan, may, and muſt vſe many points of heauenly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie. Let him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with himſelfe, in his retired thoughts,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Three points of wiſdome in reſiſting the deuill.</note>Firſt, that the deuill is exceeding ſubtill to counterfet a truce, and make as though hee were our friend, and meant vs no harme; only to make vs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:346:47"/>and heedleſſe of what wee haue to doe: for <hi>eaſe ſlaieth the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, Prou.</hi> 1.32. See the ſtraragem of the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> againſt careleſſe <hi>Laiſh,</hi> in <hi>Iudg.</hi> 18.7.27.28. then thinke vpon the deuill: and learne to ſuſpect that eſtate, which is without ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, without iealouſie, without watchfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly,
ponder vpon this, till it bee firmly ingraffed in thy minde, that the deuill is as malicious and dangerous in ſmall ſins as in great ones; in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:346:47"/>thoſe that ſeeme to fawne, as well as thoſe that make the haire ſtand on end, they are ſo odious. For why? he knowes well how to make a little ſinne a ſhooing-horn to draw on a greater. He that will be brought by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to ſweare neatly, and dallie with oathes, faith and troth, or the like, will alſo bee brought by a ſtronger occaſion to ſweare bloudily and roaring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. He that in eaſe and peace fals backe from his care and diligence
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:346:48"/>in good duties, may feare he ſhall eaſily be induced by perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to fall quite away. A ſcorner now, will be a <hi>Bonner</hi> hereafter. Theeues doubt not, if they can put in a little boy at a window, but the houſe is their own. So here. For why? A ſmall ſinne entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and cheriſhed, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleth the conſcience, ſtrengthneth corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deadeth the heart, and grieueth Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Know this, and with-ſtand Satan in ſuch, as well as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:346:48"/>ſinnes. Here is wiſdome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> let the Chriſtian thinke on this policie; that hee ſhall wiſely and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily reſiſt the deuill, if hee make a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traine, to vndermine the vnderminer: That is, let him vſe the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his power, to chaſe away the works of darkneſſe from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his familie, and the place where he liueth: alſo to ſet vp the worſhip of God in all places, and eſtabliſh it where it is, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:346:49"/>maintaine, and grace, and adorne it: for this is quite contrary to the deuils machinations. It was notable policie in <hi>Scipio,</hi> when no meanes would ſerue to driue <hi>Hannibal</hi> out of <hi>Italie,</hi> then to ſet vpon <hi>Carthage,</hi> and ſo draw him homeward, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his owne. So that Chriſtian, who is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually infeſted by the malicious tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the deuill, may deale very wiſely, if he vex him againe, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging the kingdome of grace: not only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:346:49"/>himſelfe harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, but diſaduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging this his deſperate aduerſarie by all means poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">V. Reſiſt him conſtantly.</note>Laſtly,
 reſiſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill <hi>conſtantly:</hi> not for a day, or for a moneth, or for a yeere, or two, or three, or moe, but to thy liues end.
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.28.</note> 
               <hi>Abide with Chriſt in tentation.</hi> This is the right, and the bleſſed reſiſting. What credit is it for the Lords ſouldier, to ſtand one day, and run away the next? what good, or what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, to be free to day,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:346:50"/>and a bondſlaue to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow? Therefore be aduiſed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Hauing done all, ſtand:</hi> being foiled, begin afreſh: make another skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, and another, and another: and neuer ceaſe reſiſting, till the deuill ceaſe tempting and moleſting thee, and the crowne of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt be ſet vpon thine head.</p>
            <p>This is the ſolution of the third queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 4.
 Why, and for what reaſons ſhould I reſiſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill?
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:346:50"/>and what are the grounds of this oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want abundance of arguments, to ſhew this fit and neceſſary:
 Specially in 3. heads.<note place="margin">Reaſons for reſiſtance, 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt,
conſider who is thine Antagoniſt, or the partie whom thou reſiſteſt. He is <hi>that euill one,</hi> he is <hi>Satan,</hi> he is <hi>the deuill.</hi> And either of theſe hath weight enough to vrge this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, he is <hi>that euill one,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.18. The deuill, euill many wayes.</note> exquiſitely euill, euill (according
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:346:51"/>to the deriuation of the word) with pains and induſtrie; ſo euill, that none goeth beyond him, none commeth neere him in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And he is euill, both by his wilfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from God, the chiefe good, and by a tranſcendent naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, and ſeemeth all one with his nature. Euill, by occaſioning the fall of mankinde, from the top of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to the gulfe of extreme wickedneſſe: as alſo by ſtirring vp
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:346:51"/>and drawing forth the corruption of mans heart. Euill, by diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing all the wayes he can, all that is good, both good men, and good matters: And by aiming in all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings at mans grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt euill. Now who that hath any ſparke of grace or goodneſſe in him, will not picke a quarrell againſt ſuch a one, and ſtoutly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the quarrell being once begun? Shall ſimple people be afraid of the deuill, when
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:346:52"/>they heare him deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to be a blacke grim fellow, with clawes, and hornes, and all things terrible; and ſhall not wee doe our beſt to keepe out of his clutches, when wee heare he is ſo euill, ſo incurably and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately euill?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>oſor, inimicus.</hi>
               </note> Secondly, he is <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> an enemie, an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Euil is alwaies oppoſite to good: Therefore hee whom we haue found ſo euill, muſt needs proue Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,
<note place="margin">Satan, to whom he is an enemie.</note> a ranke aduerſarie to all that good is.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:346:52"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>vnto God:</hi> He ſtretcheth his ioynts, and mainly bandeth his forces againſt the Maieſtie of God pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily and principally, and againſt others for his ſake. He maligneth that inexhauſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of infinite grace that is in him, thwart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his moſt holy and righteous counſels; diſgraceth, defaceth, and extenuateth his moſt glorious works; and ſeeketh to rob him of his glory, peculiar to himſelfe alone. Thus our Sauiour no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:346:53"/>him for an aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (<hi>Matt.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Auoid. Satan; for it is written, Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerue:)</hi> whereas before, he was only called a <hi>tempter,</hi> and the <hi>deuill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which God hath appointed for the good of his people, whether ſpirituall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, or temporall encouragements: Here he fully ſets him ſelfe to croſſe the Lord in all his intendments. He knowes, that the more
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:346:53"/>meanes he giueth vs to ſet vs forward in his ſeruice, the more hee looketh to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.48.</note> and <hi>the more he will require</hi> at our hands: and, if great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours be abuſed, the more is he diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and his ſeruants endangered. If he can get <hi>Adam</hi> to ſinne, in innocencie, in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, then he hath made a whole world of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and a hell full of fire-brands. If he can worke <hi>Dauid</hi> to adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.14.</note> and ſo to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he wounds all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:346:54"/>thorow his ſides, and makes the Name of God to be <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> greatly for his ſake. Whence would he haue had Chriſt to fall, but from a place where were ſtaires to goe downe? <hi>Caſt thy ſelfe downe from hence, Luk.</hi> 4.9. And where doth he more beſtirre himſelfe, than in places where people haue greateſt meanes of knowledge and good conſcience?</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he is an enemie <hi>to Chriſt, the promiſed ſeede,</hi> who
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:346:54"/>came into the world to <hi>deſtroy the works of the deuill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.8.</note> If hee cannot breake his head, hee will be ſtill nibbling to <hi>bruiſe his heele.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> If hee muſt not meddle with his Deitie, he will vex and torment his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. And when hee cannot ſingle with him in his owne perſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now in heauen, he will be ſure to iuſtle at his members. In the dayes of his fleſh, hee ſtil ſet vpon him either by himſelfe, or by his Agents. After that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:346:55"/>conſtict at his Inauguration, he left him but <hi>for a ſeaſon, Luk.</hi> 4.13. Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally he ſent his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to tempt him, as namely the Scribes, and Phariſes, and other petty tempters. So that his whole life was nothing elſe but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall warfare againſt the kingdome &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="3" place="margin">
                  <hi>Variè diabolus amulatus est veritatem. Tert. aduerſ Prax. c.</hi> 1</note>Thirdly, hee is an enemie <hi>to the Goſpell;</hi> to the proceedings, and the preuailing of it. Faine hee would haue ſuppreſſed it in the cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:346:55"/>and infancie of it, that it ſhould neuer haue beene preached. If that cannot be, the Preachers of it ſhall be ſet vpon on euery ſide, to make them deſiſt. If that will not fadge, falſe Apoſtles and falſe brethren ſhall be raiſed vp, to mingle falſhood with truth, and jumble together the Law and the Goſpell. If that miſchiefe be preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then he will turne himſelfe to another corner, and giue letters of commendation to the Apoſtles, to make
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:346:56"/>them ſuſpicious and odious: <hi>Act.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Theſe men are the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the moſt high God, which ſhew vnto vs the way of ſaluation.</hi> One way or other hee will hinder the pure and powerfull preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word; as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>Wee would haue come vnto you (euen I Paul) once and againe, but Satan hindred vs:</hi> If not, he will doe his beſt to hinder the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and faithfull pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the word ſo preached. Hee makes the heart of man to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:346:56"/>frame many obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt it, as, that it is either an enemie to Ciuill States, or needleſſe, or comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, or preiudiciall to his thriuing in the world, to his credit, or commoditie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> hee is an aduerſarie <hi>to eminent men,</hi> who ſtand vp in the gap, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to deale between God and his people, either in Church or Common-wealth. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> muſt be <hi>winnowed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.31.</note>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.7.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> muſt be <hi>buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by the meſſenger of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:346:57"/>Satan. Which of the Lords Worthies hath he not confronted, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and (if hee could) taken out of the Church, in any age or ſtate thereof? It grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him much, that there is any one found, who ſeeketh the weale and peace of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> One godly Miniſter in a whole country ſhall be picked out, aboue all the reſt, to be a butt of contradiction, defama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſcoffes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches. So in Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie.</p>
            <p>Fiftly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> he is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:346:57"/>
               <hi>to all good order among men, eſpecially in the beſt things.</hi> He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uieth the flouriſhing eſtate of a Chriſtian Kingdome, and doth what he can to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and blow it vp. He enuieth to people the ſetled courſe of a powerfull Miniſterie, and doth what he can to interrupt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueit. He enuieth to Chriſtians the liberties and benefits of the communion of Saints, and doth what he can to make them weary of their holy exerciſes, or
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:346:58"/>otherwiſe diſunite and ſcatter them, by arts and tricks that he will deuiſe: Whence the Apoſtle wiſheth the Corinthians to be wiſe, and temper their iuſt ſeueritie with due mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. <hi>leſt Satan get an aduantage of vs,</hi> to wit, in making the inceſtuous perſon deſpaire through ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of rigour, and conſequently hindring others from ſo ſeuere a religion. He is ready to make his beſt of any thing: Therfore looke to him, ſpoile him of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:346:58"/>his purpoſe, preſerue your liberties by all meanes poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly,
he is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie <hi>to thy ſelfe in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,</hi> in thy body, and ſoule, and goods, and friends. Hee enuieth thee euery good day that thou paſſeſt, euery benefit that thou recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt from God, and euery bit of bread that doth thee good. Hee grudgeth at thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, as ſometime at <hi>Iobs.</hi> Hee ſtill goeth about, ſeeking whom he may deuoure, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. not <hi>what,</hi> as of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:346:59"/>eſtate, but <hi>whom,</hi> as of the man. Hee oweth thee a ſpight as well as any. Then giue him as good as hee brings. Who can put vp ſo much iniurie, and bee patient? How canſt thou chuſe but reſiſt him who is an enemie to all theſe?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">The deuill ſo called in ſix reſpects.</note>But ſee further into his nature:
 In the third place, he is the deuill; that is, he is a traducer, a calumniator, an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. And this depends vpon the two former properties. For, hee that is ſo perfectly euil,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:346:59"/>and ſo ſtrongly malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as we haue ſeene, will neuer ſticke to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, and calumniate, and falſly accuſe all that he deales withall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diabolum ſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, deferen do de Deo, &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem falſum. Tert. aduerſ. Marc. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note>And firſt, <hi>hee accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God to man,</hi> telling him he is a hard Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, reapes where hee ſowed not, and gathers where he ſcattered not, as the grumbling fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the Goſpell had learned to ſpeake; and as they in the Prophet, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>What profit is it to ſerue the Lord, or to keepe his ordinances, or to walke mournfully
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:346:60"/>before him?</hi> None at all, it is altogether vaine. Or if not, yet nothing to that which Satan beſtowes vpon his ſeruants: Hee will giue a world to Chriſt, if hee will fall downe and worſhip him: Did God euer giue ſo much to one man, for one outward reuerence, at one time? Alas they are all pidling matters that he giues, nothing comparable to the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie and iollitie which is in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>hee accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth man to God,</hi> as the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:346:60"/>holy man <hi>Iob, chap.</hi> 1.9. Doth <hi>Iob</hi> feare God <hi>for nought?</hi> or is it not for his flocks of cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, and great proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie? doeſt thou thinke he loueth thee for thy ſake, and not his owne rather? And this is the nature of this curſed fiend, that he firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh vs vnto ſinne, (promiſing vs pleaſure, profit, impunitie, and ſafetie enough,) and then goeth and puts vp a bill of enditement againſt vs: firſt he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades vs from care, and conſcience, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:346:61"/>conſtancie in good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and then accuſeth vs to God, of heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hypocriſie, and diſtractedneſſe. Thence he is called <hi>the accuſer of the brethren, which accuſed them before God day and night, Reu.</hi> 12.10.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly,
<hi>he accuſeth man to man.</hi> One ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall peece of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment is, to breed diſcord and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among brethren. It is hee that ſtirreth vp iealouſie, ſuſpicions, and vncharitable ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, in one neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:346:61"/>againſt another: that he doth in malice, what proceedeth from charitie: that he infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth him of ſomewhat out of curioſitie, not out of conſcience: that he affecteth a peeuiſh ſingularitie in matter of religion, and not obedience to God. He ſaith to one man of another, as the Nobles ſaid to <hi>Hanun</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Dauid,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.3.</note> Doth Dauid indeed reſpect Hanun?</hi> canſt thou thinke hee loueth thee in deed and in truth? Still he caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſuch bones, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murres,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:346:62"/>to ſeparate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene deare friends.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly,
<hi>he accuſeth man to himſelfe.</hi> It he be an holy man, one that feareth God, and endeuoureth to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the way of godlineſſe, he will make him beleeue, that he is but an hypocrite in all he doth, not a iot of ſinceritie is in him; therefore a caſt-away, a reprobate, a firebrand of hell. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: If a man be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and diſſolute, and looketh not which end goeth forward in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:346:62"/>things of his ſoule, him he will make be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that his eſtate is better than it is; oh he is out of all hazzard, cocke-ſure of eternall life, and what need he feare? Iuſt like the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers of the tyrant <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> who would licke vp his ſpettle, and proteſt it was as ſweet as <hi>Nectar</hi> or <hi>Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> the food of their gods. Thus all the ſinnes of the godly are <hi>mortall,</hi> and cannot be pardoned; al the ſins of the wicked are <hi>veniall,</hi> &amp; cannot be puniſhed.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:346:63"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, the deuill <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth vertues for vices, and vices for vertues;</hi> and makes men fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that curſe of the Prophet, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Woe vnto them that call good euill, and euill good, that put darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe; that put bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter.</hi> What now adayes is forwardneſſe in religion accounted, but fooliſh giddineſſe? and what luke-warme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but diſcreet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration? How often is extreme earthlineſſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:346:63"/>ſhrowded vnder the name of good husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, and pride vnder the name of decencie, and apiſhneſſe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements vnder the name of good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and exceſſiue prodigalitie vnder the name of good nature? Who hath taught this ſtrange impoſition of new names, but that <hi>Grand Lier,</hi> the maſter of falſhood?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, <hi>he accuſeth in his inſtruments.</hi> The deuill maketh men to bee accuſers, ſyco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants, picke-thanks,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:346:64"/>deuils, (as the word ſtandeth in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Such was <hi>Doeg</hi> againſt <hi>Dauid, Ziba</hi> againſt <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth,</hi> the falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt Chriſt, and thoſe wicked wretches who infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Heathen Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperors,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. hiſt. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> that the Chriſtians of the Primitiue Church affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a temporall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe them of their throne, vnleſſe they were the better lookt vnto.</p>
            <p>Now doth Satan
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:346:64"/>thus ſay and vnſay, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and change, put in and put out, and turne things vpſide downe, that we cannot ſee the truth of our eſtate as we ſhould? Who then would not reſiſt this accuſer, this traducer, this ſlanderer, this broacher of lies, and maſter of miſſe-rule?</p>
            <p>Adde vnto all this, that he is one who will not be ouercome by faire meanes: there is no winning of a deuill with kindneſſe: that will not ſerue the turn: Hee will ouerthrow
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:346:65"/>thee, if thou doe not ouerthrow and chaſe him away. Therefore reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>State precor ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri memores, memores quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Chriſti: Quae ſit veſtra tribus, quae gloria, quis Deus, &amp; Rex, Quis Dominus, meminiſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. Prudent. in Pſychom.</hi>
               </note>Next conſider, who thy ſelfe art, that muſt make reſiſtance vpon Satan. Who art thou? Thou art a man, a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creature: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as a man, prouide as well as thou canſt, for thine owne ſafetie. Thou art a ſinner, <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the ſnare of the deuill, and led captiue by him to doe his will,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. therefore deliuer thy ſelfe, as a bird out of the ſnare of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:346:65"/>the fowler. Thou art a Chriſtian; therefore muſt partake of Chriſts powerfull grace and anointing, and bee a King, to conquer his and thine enemies. Thou art a baptized perſon, and vowedſt enmitie againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, when thou recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedſt the ſeale of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and entredſt into the Church: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore performe the word of an honeſt man. Thou art one of the Angels of <hi>Michael;</hi> therefore muſt fight with him againſt the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:346:66"/>dragon and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. And one of a band of Lions; for <hi>the righteous are bold as Lions, Prou.</hi> 28.1. The ſame combat is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by thy brethren <hi>abroad in the world,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9. therefore reſiſt ſtedfaſtly (it is the Apoſtles argument) and ſtand it out: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one dieth in the field by cowardly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times another, but the Lords Champions goe ſtill away with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Finally, conſider we 
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:346:66"/>what miſchiefe hee would bring vpon vs,
<note place="margin">Miſchiefes of being foiled.</note> if he could once foile vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Priuatiue.</note>Firſt,  all the liueli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods of a Chriſtian, all his graces, and all his aſſurances, hee would quite take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. His deſire is,
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.31, 32</note> to <hi>winnow</hi> the Saints, and make their <hi>faith faile:</hi> that by the failing thereof, all the <hi>labours</hi> of a godly Miniſterie may bee <hi>loſt,</hi> as the Apoſtle inferreth, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.5. Or if hee cannot bring them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to flat infidelitie, hee
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:346:67"/>will ſeeke to pull them from that integritie and <hi>ſimplicitie</hi> which becomes the Goſpell of God our Sauiour, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. Hee will endeuour to make them vaine, formall, hypocriticall, fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, or vnfruitfull; or to draw them from their conſtancie in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and reſiſting euill. And hereby he aimes at their ſpirituall beggerie, that is, to rob them of all their hopes, and comforts, and aſſurances, all the ioyes of the holy
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:346:67"/>Ghoſt and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the kingdome of heauen. Now, ſhall a man fight for his purſe, or goods, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt for ſo great a patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Saints?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Poſitiue.</note>Secondly, all euill followeth immediatly vpon thy ouerthrow. For now thou art the deuils owne childe, an vtter enemie to God and the things of God, furious and outragious by little and little, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately euill, &amp; heire of condemnation, like thy father himſelfe in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:346:68"/>ſinne and puniſhment, and thy torments ſhall be endleſſe, eaſleſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe.</p>
            <p>Reſiſt therefore, and betimes preuent ſo great miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>And thus the foure queſtions are fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, both for clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the point, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the Chriſtian Warriour. Let vs now deſcend to the vſes hereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">A reproofe &amp; diſgrace to the eaſie life of many.</note>And firſt, this ſerues to bring out of requeſt the ſecure and eaſie condition of many people, who neither
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:346:68"/>doe, nor wil, nor thinke they haue need to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect themſelues. Wee may well ſay of them with the Prophet,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>They haue no bands vpon them, either in their life or death, neither doe they come into trouble as other men;</hi> They are fat, and ſtrong, and liuely, and in very good liking; They haue the world at will, and more indeed than heart can deſire; All admire, and follow, and attend them, and ſpeake well of them, Oh the only men in
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:346:69"/>towne or country: and they can thinke, and ſpeake of others, and doe to them what themſelues pleaſe, yet all muſt be well.</p>
            <p>Others of a meaner ranke can ſpend their dayes iollily, and ſmoothly, and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly; neighbourly men, &amp; good Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers; not only giue way to religion, but ſome countenance; and ſo pop into their graue, as fruit gathered when it is ripe.</p>
            <p>And doe you diſlike or condemn this eſtate,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:346:69"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide ne fortè ideo non ſit bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, quia pax peruerſa eſt. Aug. de verbis Apoſt. ſerm.</hi> 12.</note>will ſome man ſay? I anſwer, Yes,
 and I haue iuſt cauſe ſo to doe: for it is as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a condition as thoſe who are openly prophane, if not more. But howſoeuer, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be good, it cannot be ſafe. For, hath not the opening of this text diſcouered, that the life of a Chriſtian here is the life of a ſouldier? Haue we not heard of warre, and fighting, and ſtriuing, and reſiſting? And haue wee not ſeene, that this buſtling is grounded vpon rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:346:70"/>very ſufficient? Whence then is this generall careleſneſſe, and vniuerſall vnfee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth the hearts of the ſonnes of men? Is it indeed a pleaſant, or an eaſie thing to be a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour? No trouble, no feare, no diſtraction in a campe? No wounds, or bloudſhed in an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie? Were hee not a foole that would goe into a battell aray, and yet ſay,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>Peace, Peace, where there can bee no peace?</hi> Examine the matter by common
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:346:70"/>reaſon, and you ſhall finde it euidently true. Then looke backe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Satan, and thinke if you <hi>can,</hi> that he is more idle or weake to follow his skirmiſh, than men are to follow theirs. Nay, he is more mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, more puiſſant, more vnweariable. No truce can be taken, no fauour expected, no conditions of peace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, vnleſſe wee yeeld him all that hee asketh: and, what that is, let any one iudge.</p>
            <p>Therefore (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) let theſe things
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:346:71"/>worke vpon our hearts, and perſwade vs for time to come to fight, and fight valiantly. Let vs know, that wee haue a moſt peſtilent, and terrible, and bloud-thirſtie enemie. And knowing it, we cannot in reaſon but doe our beſt to preuent his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. Let vs be ſober, and temperate in all things, not ſuffering our ſelues to be clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with any diſtract-full hindrances, within vs, or without vs; as they that run in a race, and <hi>ſtriue for the maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25.</note>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:346:71"/>And not only be ſober, but watch, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Be ſober, be vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant.</hi> And not only ſo, but pray, <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Watch and pray, that yee enter not into tentation.</hi> And more than that, <hi>Endure hardneſſe, as a good ſouldier of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Be not entangled with the affaires of this life, ſtriue lawfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">A caueat to the godly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſſe.</note>Secondly, this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth as an antidote, or preſeruatiue to the children of God, to keepe them holily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in that ranke
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:346:72"/>wherein the Lord hath placed them. Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it commeth to paſſe through the weakneſſe of their fleſh, and the heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſpirit, and the occaſions they haue in the world, and their familiaritie with good duties, that they doe euen ſtand at a ſtay, and know not well which way to turne themſelues. To ioyne with prophane ones, they dare not, they cannot: it is againſt their profeſſion, and conſcience, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:346:72"/>And to exceed themſelues in the work of holineſſe, they know not how. They are ſure, that more grace ſhould and may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but wherein, or how? Thus in a maze (as it were) and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full what to doe, they eaſily incline to a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate mediocritie, and reſt content with ſome of the <hi>power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note> but more of the <hi>forme</hi> of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Grace they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſtill to purſue, but without due affection: Holy exerciſes they will ſtill obſerue, both
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:346:73"/>at home &amp; at Church, but coldly, ſleepily, brokenly, vnfeelingly, vnfruitfully.</p>
            <p>This lukewarmneſſe of theirs, carnall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſee, and laugh at it: themſelues ſee, and bewaile it, and wiſh it were with them as ſometimes it was at their firſt conuerſion; to bee forward, and zealous, and doe the worke of the Lord di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently. But how may this be, or what ſhould they doe?</p>
            <p>Here now I anſwer by vertue of this text,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:346:73"/>
               <hi>Reſiſt the deuill.</hi> Many meanes they haue to ſhake vp their ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: as for example, To conſider deeply and ſeriouſly the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and hainouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſinnes, both before their rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and ſince: To recount their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme beggerie in themſelues, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe to receiue the leaſt fauour from the Lord: To prize highly the bloud of the Couenant where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: and the like. But
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:346:74"/>eſpecially let them be carefull to remember, and carry in minde, this neceſſary doctrine of the <hi>Chriſtian War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</hi> For, if the noiſe of drums and trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, if the fourbiſhing of ſwords, and the glittering of armour, and the trailing of pikes, will not ſtirre vp a mans ſpirits, what will? This therefore let the Chriſtian man conſider, and thus let him ſay with himſelfe:</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>What? haue I no enemie, with whom to exerciſe my ſelfe?
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:346:74"/>Are there no deuils abroad in the world or in hell? Hath my purſe enemies on the high-way, and my goods enemies about my houſe; and my body ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and my ſoule no enemies? Much adoe I finde in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and keeping a ſmall worldly eſtate about me: and doth it aske no feare or paines, to get and keepe poſſeſſion of the kingdome of heauen? What? no oppoſition? Did all
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:346:75"/>the earth ſit ſtill,
<note place="margin">Zech. 1.11, 12.</note> and at reſt, while <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> was vnder an heauie indignation, threeſcore and ten yeeres; and ſhall I, who profeſſe my ſelfe one of the citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the new <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſit ſtill, and at reſt, while the whole world of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers is hot in the battell? How doth this hang together? Should I not weepe with them that weepe, and be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie with them that ſorrow? Haue I not
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:346:75"/>too iuſt cauſe ſo to doe?</p>
               <p> Why, what doe I thinke of Satan? Is he ſo louing, that he will ſpare me, or ſo weake, that he will feare me? Is he wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that he cannot deceiue me by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie, or idle, that he will not? Was hee too good for our firſt parents in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, for <hi>Noah</hi> a Patriarke, for <hi>Dauid</hi> a Prophet, for <hi>Peter</hi> an Apoſtle, for <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> an Euangeliſt, for <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:346:76"/>two famous Profeſſors, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Worthies of the Lord? and is it not likely hee will get ground of me? Me? Alas ſilly creature that I am! who am I, to ſtand in the hands of ſo ſtout a Champion, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vnarmed!</p>
               <p>Therfore hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, O my ſoule, and all that is within me, muſter vp your forces, and come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field. I haue hitherto ſpotted, &amp; ſlept, and ſnorted in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:346:76"/>the cradle of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: I little dreamt of an enemie, at leaſt to be ſo neere as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he is, like <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Abner</hi> in the campe when <hi>Dauid</hi> might haue ſmote off their heads, 1 <hi>Sa.</hi> 26.8.15. An hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to one, but I had beene deſtroied ere this time. Oh bleſſed be God who hath deliuered mee out of the mouth of the Lion, and the paw of the Beare, and hath giuen mee time to ſee mine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour!
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:346:77"/>By the grace of my Lord Ieſus, I will hereafter keepe more conſtantly to my colours, &amp; fight vnder the bannet of my owne Lord.</p>
               <p>Thus therefore I argue: Is he a fox, and not ſubtill? Is he a ſerpent, and not wilie? and, if hee be ſubtill &amp; wilie, hath he no feats or tricks to put vpon mee? Becauſe I in ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie thinke <hi>him</hi> no harme, doth hee thinke <hi>mee</hi> none? Is he not now at this
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:346:77"/>preſent time, about ſome ſtratageme to vndermine mee? Doth hee not lay ſiege to the Caſtle of my ſoule, either to ſcale the walls of my faith, or to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the bulwarke of my patience, or to pull downe the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets of my zeale and fortitude? Hath hee not ſome fetch or other, to draw mee from my hold, and then ſome ambuſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſurpriſe me vnawares? Yes: he hath a thouſand
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:346:78"/>wayes to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſuch a ſimple freſh-water ſouldier as I am: as many turnings and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, as anſractu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Meandrus;</hi> as many heads as the ſerpent <hi>Hydra,</hi> as many eyes as the neuer-ſleeping <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi> Therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Philiſtims are ſtill ready to come vpon me, and binde me if I ſleepe, I will ſurely looke vnto them, I will vp and ſhake my ſelfe, and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:346:78"/>follow my Chriſten courſe more warily, more watchfully.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Lord grant that thou maieſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, let this be a word of exhortation to all of vs, ſo to reſiſt the deuill, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t he may flie from vs. The moſt hold it fit to reſiſt him; but few agree vpon the right manner. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs deale tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly in this buſineſſe, and neuer reſt till wee know wee reſiſt as wee ought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> How may I know that?</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:346:79"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Markes of right reſiſting the deuill.</note>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, if thou <hi>reſiſteſt thine owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and rebellious fleſh,</hi> by mortification, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable vſe of holy meanes. For the deuill and our owne fleſh are of the ſame kinde in reſpect of ſinne, and fight equally againſt the ſoule: as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Abſtaine from fleſhly luſts, which warre againſt the ſoule:</hi> and <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Luſts warre in the members.</hi> This is an home-bred enemie, lurking within our
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:346:79"/>owne walls. Of it ſelfe it worketh many ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems againſt vs, by mouing to the acts of pride, malice, reuenge, oppreſſion, contempt of the Goſpell, and the like. And the deuill is no readier to craue its aſſiſtance, than it is to afford it: working ſlily as he doth, and ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: that the Chriſtian almoſt needs not to aske that queſtion, How ſhall I diſcerne the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan from the euill mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mine owne heart? Some difference
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:346:80"/>there is, and a deuill may be eſpied by the ſuddenneſſe, and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raineſſe, and importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie of his ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The motions of nature are more ſlow, and more ſutable with nature, and not ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently purſued as thoſe are. But for the moſt part, we need not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue any ſuch diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; the fleſh eaſily agreeing with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and the deuill ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his temptations to the deſire of the fleſh.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:346:80"/>
            <p>This a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian knowes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he lookes home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward principally: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeeing the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cannot foile him without himſelfe, but himſelfe can deſtroy himſelfe without the deuill. So that well was it ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ier. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>The heart of man is deceitfull and wicked aboue all things,</hi> euen aboue that foule ſpirit, as foule and as blacke as he is.</p>
            <p>Some ſay of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 8.2.</note> that <hi>ſeuen deuils</hi> were caſt out of her, that is, ſeuen dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:346:81"/>ſinnes, pride, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and the reſt. And we may almoſt ſay, So many ſinnes as thou cheriſheſt and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quot peecata, tot daemonia.</hi>
               </note> willingly and with delight of thy heart, ſo many deuils thou lodgeſt vnder the roofe of the houſe of thy ſoule.
<note place="margin">Matt. 12.43.</note> They are <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirits,</hi> becauſe they beare rule ouer men by the vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their hearts and liues.</p>
            <p>Now examine thy ſelfe by this marke. So truly and faithfully as thou watcheſt againſt
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:346:81"/>the corruptions of thy nature, ſo truly and faithfully thou reſiſteſt the deuill. And thoſe are eaſily proued liers, who ſay they defie and ſcorne the deuill, yet obey their owne luſts, vſe no diſcipline to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their vnrulie hearts, but take their owne ſwindge in any or all vngodlineſſe: No, no, they agree with him well enough: he deſireth no better weapons againſt vs, than thoſe out of our owne armourie.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteſt
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:346:82"/>the deuill, ſo long as thou <hi>deſirest to reſiſt:</hi> and this deſire is euer accompanied with care and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. None in the Lords field is yet ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, who deſireth to ouercome; yea they that fall by the ſleights of Satan, and are taken away by violence, yet falling in this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.4.</note> and <hi>reſiſting vnto bloud,</hi> they are ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, and more than conquerors. God, who accepteth the will for the deed, accepteth the faithfull purpoſe of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:346:82"/>reſiſtance for reſiſtance it ſelfe, euen when the Tempter doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what preuaile, &amp; make battery vpon the ſoule. Chriſt taketh notice of the willingneſſe of the ſpirit in his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Matt. 26.41.</note> when hee ſeeth great weakneſſe in their fleſh.</p>
            <p>And this note ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth principally for the comfort of afflicted ſoules, which crie out of themſelues as foiled, and ſuch as haue caſt vp the buckler to the deuill, in way of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary yeelding; yet
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:346:83"/>minding to goe on in the skirmiſh as truſtily as euer, and keeping the ſame way as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. They muſt know, that their caſe is good enough, and they ſhall be accepted <hi>according to what they haue,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12.</note> and not according to what they haue not;</hi> yea ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which they deſire to haue. A man in warre that is halfe dead, doth what he can againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, by ſpurning, by ſupplanting, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: And ſo doe you againſt the grand ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:346:83"/>of your ſoules, therefore ſhall not bee accounted to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted, but ſhall bee crowned as well as the reſt, and (it may bee) among the firſt. Only continue this deſire, care ſtill to maintaine the Lords right, and watch ſtill to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the aduerſarie: This ſhall be reckoned to you for perfection of valour.</p>
            <p>The third marke of reſiſtance is this:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>If thou grieueſt when thou art foiled, and ſeekeſt to recouer thy ſelfe, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:346:84"/>make amends by better truſtineſſe.</hi> Vndoe the works of the deuill, by morning for them, by repentance, by run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the enſignes of Chriſt, and by doing the contrary works, of what kinde ſoeuer: and now know thou haſt reſiſted. For the deuils purpoſe is, that thou ſhouldeſt continue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a foile; and hee knowes, that if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get thee to lie ſtill in the ſinne commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it will doe him no good, nor thee harme. It is one kinde of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:346:84"/>to recouer our ſelues after our falls. Otherwiſe, which of the Lords Worthies did euer reſiſt him?
<note place="margin">1 Chron. 21.1. 2 Sam. 24.1.</note> Satan ſtirred vp <hi>Dauid</hi> to number the people, and he numbred them; which was his great ſinne, ſo mortally pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: but <hi>Dauids</hi> heart ſmote him for this fact, and hee made his recantation, ſaying, <hi>I have ſinned,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> I haue done wickedly, let thine hand be against me, and my fathers houſe:</hi> and ſo Satan was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſappointed of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:346:85"/>his malicious proiect againſt him.</p>
            <p>The fourth marke is:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>If thou art troubled when thou ſeeſt the works of darkneſſe goe forward, and gladded to ſee any thing on foot that ouerthrowes the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the deuill.</hi> For he that reſiſteth him aright, would haue him reſiſted and reiected euery where, by others as well as by himſelfe: hee would haue none obey him, or ſubmit to his gouernment: he is a rebell, and an vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and therefore why
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:346:85"/>ſhould hee haue any place, to rule in any parts of the Lords ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories? <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>When the righteous are in authoritie, the people reioyce: but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourne, Prouerb.</hi> 29.2. We may applie it to this: A good man is ſorrowfull, when he ſeeth any ſent into a place, either for Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie or Miniſterie, who is likely to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance Poperie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and weaken the hands of the godly, to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:346:86"/>hearten the wicked, and doe miſchiefe any way among ſimple people; or when hee ſeeth the people them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſet vpon wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. It is euen a death to him, and his zeale doth almoſt <hi>conſume</hi> him,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.9. Ioh. 2.17.</note> as is ſaid of <hi>Dauid</hi> and our Sauiour. And on the contrary, it is ioy to his heart, to heare or ſee a good man come into a place where hee may doe good, or hinder euill; to ſee a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſet ouer a people, or good orders taken
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:346:86"/>for the curbing of ſin. For now he hopes the power of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe muſt totter, and now it is likely the ſtrong holds of the ſtrong man ſhall bee caſt downe, &amp; much good will be done in ſuch a place. Therefore hee cannot but reioyce: why ſhould hee not? And while he doth ſo reioyce, hee hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe of ioy in this alſo, that he is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to the deuill, and the deuill to him.</p>
            <p>The ſift marke is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:346:87"/>
               <hi>Care in the vſe of the meanes, whereby the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill is reſiſted.</hi> He that vſeth phyſicke, reſiſteth the diſeaſe: and hee that is conſcionable in ſharpning the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all weapons before mentioned, doth reſiſt the deuill. So much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence as a man vſeth in ſearching, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, and laying vp the word, in ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his faith, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming his hope, in fortifying his patience; ſo much as hee ſtriueth in praier, to be conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour; ſo much as hee
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:346:87"/>endeuoureth to keepe his conſcience cleare, and to keepe with the Lords armies, by whom the ſame skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes are fulfilled: ſo much ſinceritie he hath in following this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with the deuill. And they that ſay they reſiſt him, yet neglect theſe weapons, care not for the word read or preached, thinke not of increaſing their faith, or any of thoſe graces, nor make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of holy exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, doe lie in ſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Though they
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:346:88"/>ſhould ſpet ſo long, that they ſpet out their lungs, yet the deuill would not flie from them; but keepe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and that quietly enough. For he is not expelled, but by diuine authoritie and power. Hee that meaneth to foile him indeed, will ſo conſider, and be ſo diligent in vſing the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued meanes of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
            <p>The ſixt marke is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>Feare leſt thou reſiſteſt not in the due manner.</hi> This a careleſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian neuer hath: yea
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:346:88"/>he is more confident in his ſtrawes and toies, than the godly is in weilding the armour ſet apart by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For moſt part, a carnall man thinketh not of reſiſting the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, till he is euen rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to fall headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his condemnation, and then he beſtirreth himſelfe, after his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. Or he can ſee the deuill in his owne wicked practiſe, but it is after the ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, rather than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: And not in ſmall ſinnes, but in great and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:346:89"/>crying ſins only, which the world taketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, or ſuch as bring preſent puniſhment, &amp; ſhame among men. Or if he begin at any time to reſiſt the deuill, hee doth it ſo faintly, and ſillily, and by halues, that hee neuer getteth out of his clut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And when he is moſt in heart, together with ſome watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that againſt all ſinnes as he think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, yet then he is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, and leeſeth the victorie one day which hee got the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:346:89"/>But howſoeuer, in all his ſtriuing, euen at the beſt, hee is neuer fearfull or iealous ouer his deceitfull heart, but thinkes hee doth well enough, and he doubts not at all. Whereas a true Chriſtian feares he doth not as he ſhould, and recompenceth his failing in the <hi>matter,</hi> by his care in the <hi>manner</hi> of reſiſting the deuill.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth marke is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               <hi>Vnfained thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to Chriſt; who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſtrength to reſiſt, and to ouercome.</hi> This is a ſigne, that we reſiſt
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:346:90"/>vpon a good ground, and by a right power; not by our owne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe; or skilfulneſſe. We acknowledge wee are of our ſelues ſilly, &amp; inſufficient for ſuch a combat, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, after it is finiſhed, we muſt not liue to our ſelues, or ſacrifice to our owne yarne, as if our owne bow and ſword had ſaued vs; but as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.3. <hi>Thy right hand, and thine arme, and the light of thy countenance becauſe thou badſt a fauour vnto
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:346:90"/>vs:</hi> therefore to thee will we liue, for thee will we die. Thus the Saints caſt all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the victorie vpon Chriſt, their head and commander, <hi>Reu.</hi> 5.10, 11, 12. <hi>Thou haſt redeemed vs to God by thy bloud, and haſt made vs Kings and Prieſts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and wee ſhall reigne on the earth,</hi> &amp;c. They ouercome the dragon by the <hi>bleud of the Lambe. Reu.</hi> 12.11. &amp; therefore the Lambe ſhall haue the honour of their conqueſt. And they will ſpecially ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:346:91"/>their thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in holineſſe of life, obſeruing the lawes of their Generall, and keeping within his campe, and vnder his banner, without muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, outrage, filthineſſe, or any vnbeſeeming behauiour. But where it is otherwiſe, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill is not rightly reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. Where Chriſt gets no honour in an holy and refined conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he neuer aſſiſted ſuch againſt Satan. For, wherefore are wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed out of the hand of our enemies,
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.74, 75.</note>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:346:91"/>but that wee ſhould ſerue our Redeemer in holineſſe and true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe all the dayes of our life?</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> this may be ſome ſtay to a troubled and afflicted heart: <hi>If the deuill reſiſteth thee, thou reſiſteſt him:</hi> yea, therefore hee reſiſteth thee, becauſe thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteſt him. For he figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not with his own: why ſhould he? or to what end? While the ſtrong man keepeth poſſeſſion, all is in peace: as while the Iaylor hath his priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:346:92"/>ſure enough, hee lets them lie together in quietneſſe enough. But, as hee beſtirreth himſelfe, if any of them giue him the ſlip, ſo if any man at any time begin to get out of the power of Satan, by whom hee was taken captiue at his pleaſure to doe his will, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vproares and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults are made, and the deuill hath officers euery where (wicked and vngodly men) who will vſe all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in ſending <hi>Huy and cry</hi> after the eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:346:92"/>Chriſtian; and, if either violence, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie, or promiſes, or threats, or any thing will reduce him to his ancient bondage, hee ſhall not long continue a free man.</p>
            <p>Take this therefore for a note of oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the deuill, if he maintaine oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt thee.
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Count it all ioy, when thou fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt into diuers temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Though they be troubleſome and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to a holy heart, which hateth and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth them, &amp; would
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:346:93"/>faine be rid of them, yet haue they their vſe alſo for good, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Chriſtian by ſtrong conſequence, that his eſtate is ſafe enough, and ſo long as he continueth making reſiſtance, he need not feare. A happie man he is, that ſeeth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill profeſſing himſelfe his enemie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label>
               <note place="margin">A cenſure of ſcorners, who diſlike ſuch diſcourſes.</note>Fourthly, we ſee by all this, how wide they are from the right, who like not ſuch trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, ſuch practiſes, ſuch care in examining ones ſelfe; but ieſt, and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:346:93"/>ſcoffe, and put off all this ſo neceſſarie a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with a ſcornfull tuſh. Tuſh (ſaith one) what doe you tell vs of a deuill? when did you ſee him? and how doe you know him ſo well? and why doe you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright people with ſuch words of terrour? And Tuſh (ſaith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) what needs all this preaching about this matter? a goodly Sermon! and, Hee names the deuill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at euery word. So ſome haue ſaid of the former diſcourſes,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:346:94"/>ſimple and blindfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded creatures that they are: The Lord open their eyes, that they may ſee how <hi>the god of this world hath blinded them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4.</note> and get out of his ſnare. But others haue a tuſh too, and it is caſt againſt them that are ſo carefull in reſiſting the deuill, as wee haue proued all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhould be: Oh it is a fit of melancholie, a ſilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a childiſhneſſe: and, What man, take a good heart, put ſuch thoughts out of your minde, Come, follow
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:346:94"/>the world as wee doe, make your ſelfe merry, and leaue theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth cogitations to them that are ſo pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note this.</hi>
               </note>But ſtay, O man: this is not to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the deuill, but to <hi>ſcorne</hi> him. If this troubled perſon ſhould take this counſell, he ſhould not ouercome this grand enemie of his ſoule, but take truce with him, and ſo, by pleaſing himſelfe in a fond and vaine peace, ſhould loſe his owne ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as thou in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:346:95"/>muſt loſe thine. Therefore bee aduiſed what thou wilt doe: theſe are no ieſting matters: Heare what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Reſiſt the deuill,</hi> and for time to come yeeld it a duty both lawfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God ſhould thus care, and labour, and ſtriue in reſiſting, and thou with them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label>
               <note place="margin">This heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the godly.</note>Finally, here is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for them that ſo reſiſt the deuill. And it ſhall be of worth, againſt all calumnies
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:346:95"/>and ſcoffes of thoſe ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whatſoeuer they be. Know (O ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Lord) that you are in the right way. You haue rightly iudged of your life, to be (as it is) a warfare. You fight the good fight of faith, and are ſure of victorie; which, when it is atchieued, there is a crowne of righteouſneſſe prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of old, which ſhall certainly be put vpon your heads. You take Gods part againſt his and your enemies, and therefore he will take
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:346:96"/>your part, ſuſtaining you, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iling them. You are the Angels of <hi>Michael,</hi> and ſhall ſee the time, when the great dragon (the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill) ſhall be quite caſt out, and vtterly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from heauen, no more to moleſt, and vex, and diſquiet your righteous ſoules. And for the preſent, during the time of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, know for your comfort, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his wiles, and tricks, and cloſe following of his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet vpon your
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:346:96"/>reſiſtance hee muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid and be gone. If you vſe the armour deſcribed, and vſe it in the due manner before ſpoken of, hee cannot ſtand before you. So often as he giueth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, doe you giue him battell; and then leane vpon this faithfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, full of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which comes now to be handled)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he will flie from you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond generall part of this text.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The euent of other battels is doubtfull, victorie altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine: Though the
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:346:97"/>cauſe be good, and the men valorous, &amp; ſtand the field ſtoutly, yet they may goe away vanquiſhed, as the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites a long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Beniamites. But here the conqueſt is certaine: before any ſtroke is giuen, wee know wee ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: euery one that will reſiſt, ſhall chaſe away his enemie, though himſelfe be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo weake, his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie neuer ſo ſtrong and puiſſant.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But how may wee vnderſtand this flight
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:346:97"/>of the deuill? and how doth he flie away, who is ſo inceſſant in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations?</p>
            <p>I anſwer: Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>I</label>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homil.</hi> 7. <hi>in Ioſue.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> thinkes, that the Saints of God, reſiſting the helliſh tempters when they prouoke vnto euill, doe dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the armie of the deuils, and (as it were) kill many of them: ſo that it is not lawfull for that ſpirit, which is ouercome of an holy man, liuing chaſtly and graciouſly, againe to ſet vpon any other man. But this is not
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:346:98"/>ſo: for the ſame deuill, which had beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by our Sauiour in his firſt temptation, did trie him with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and a third.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſecondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> others (by the relation of <hi>Lombard</hi>) thinke,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>diſtinct.</hi> 5 <hi>H. lit.</hi>
               </note> that this of <hi>Origen</hi> muſt be vnderſtood only of that vice, wherein the foule ſpirit was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: as for example, If he ſollicit any good man vnto pride, and be foiled, hee may not againe ſollicit vnto pride, either the ſame man, or any other. But
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:346:98"/>this is wholly vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and not materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to the comfort of a Chriſtian; as our text doth intend. For if one deuill ſhould leaue ſuch a ſinfull motion, another would follow it, and diſquiet him as much as the other could poſſibly; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally there being ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny legions of them, one to ſucceed another in their miſchieuous intendments. And what cares the deuill, by what ſinne he gains a ſoule, if hee may be ſure to gaine it? Either
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:346:99"/>of the extremes will ſerue his turne ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently: or an habituall neglect of good, as well as the wilfull perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of euill.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">A twofold flight of the deuill.</note>Therefore thirdly, the plaine anſwer is this: There is a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold flying away, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon the deuill by the power of God, and this his promiſe: One partiall and tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the other totall and finall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Partiall and temporary.</note>
               <hi>That,</hi> when the child of God is enabled by the wiſdome and grace of God, to reiect any
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:346:99"/>wicked ſuggeſtion, and ſo is rid of the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for that time: and, ſo often as the deuill reneweth his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo often the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reneweth his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, in reſiſting him, and therefore ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth conquerour. The deuill left Chriſt but <hi>for a ſeaſon, Luk.</hi> 4.13. and no longer doth hee leaue the members of Chriſt. He goeth away, and returneth, and then muſt goe away againe, and ſo continueth paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to and fro, beaten
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:346:100"/>and ouerthrowne ſo often as he is reſiſted. Faine he would return and re-enter into his old houſe, to take and keepe more ſure poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion: but if a repulſe be giuen him, he muſt take the repulſe, and flie away.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <note place="margin">Totall and finall.</note>
               <hi>This,</hi> that is, the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and finall flight of the deuill is at the end of the warfare, and of the Chriſtians life, when he moſt beſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe, becauſe his <hi>time is but ſhort,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 12.12.</note> and he would faine lay hold on the righteous
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:346:100"/>ſoule which hee long moleſted, to carry it among his own fiends, in eternall torments. Here he is preuented of his purpoſe perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The Spirit of God aſſiſteth the Chriſtian heart, and vpholdeth it with faith, with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the promiſes, with the ſenſe of Gods mercy, and all conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſupplies, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeuerall and particular occaſions.
<note place="margin">Luk. 16.22.</note> And at laſt the Angels take the ſoule (as the ſoule of <hi>Lazarus</hi>) and
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:346:101"/>carry it into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, in endleſſe bleſſedneſſe. And now the whole skirmiſh is finiſhed, the field won, the good fight of faith fought to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and the deuill fled away for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>The point is this:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">The deuill, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, fleeth neceſſarily.</note>
               <hi>All the Lords Warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, who reſiſt the deuill as they ought, ſhall ouercome, and be rid of him.</hi> They are as ſure of victorie, as of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. His preſence is not ſo tedious and tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but his abſence
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:346:101"/>(which is moſt certain) ſhall be as ioyous and comfortable. We fight not at vncertaintie, but know wee ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. It was for want of reſiſtance, that our firſt parents were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and are of the forbidden tree: that <hi>Dauid</hi> lifted vp his heart, and numbred the people: that <hi>Iudas</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed his Maſter, and ſo fell into his owne place: and, that euer any was ſubdued by the deuil, was for want of reſiſtance. They that would ouercome, did
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:346:102"/>ouercome, and could not be foiled. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour reſiſted, and ſaw the deuill flying from him. The Apoſtles and Diſciples reſiſted, and ſaw him fall like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from heauen. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reſiſted, and found grace ſufficient againſt the meſſenger of Satan that buffeted him. In a word, all the Angels of <hi>Michael</hi> that fought againſt the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, did ſo thruſt him to the walls, that hee was caſt out, and his place found no more. Where the Chriſtian
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:346:102"/>findes a heart &amp; hands, the deuill muſt finde wings and heeles. And why?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe of the faithfull promiſe of the mightie God, who is able to doe this for vs, and hath ſaid hee will doe it. And hee hath ſaid ſo, both here, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the deuill, and <hi>he will flie from you;</hi> and elſewhere, <hi>The God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan vnder your feet ſhortly, Rom.</hi> 16.20. where the Apoſtle ſpeakes of them that are wiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good, and ſimple
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:346:103"/>concerning euil; which is all one with reſiſting of the deuill. To ſuch he is a God of peace, and will in a little time put an end to all their conflicts. For, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is he that hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, who alſo will doe it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vincatur neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe eſt, quia Chriſtus quem confitemur, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uictus eſt. Cyp. de exhort. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi>
               </note>Secondly, the valour of our Captain is ſuch, that the enemie cannot ſtand before him or vs. He himſelfe, by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, did in ſingle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat put him to the worſe, and made him auoid: by whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and conqueſt wee
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:346:103"/>alſo ſhall goe away vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. Wee goe not forth againſt theſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh wickedneſſes, in our owne name and ſtrength, but in the name and ſtrength of God, &amp; by the power of Chriſt, who was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ouercome yet, but ouercame in euery skirmiſh. <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.11. <hi>They ouercame him by the bloud of the Lambe.</hi> And hereof wee may aſſure our ſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſet foot out of our tents and campe; as the Church of old, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 44.5. <hi>Through
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:346:104"/>thee will we puſh downe our enemies: through thy Name will we tread them vnder, that riſe vp against vs.</hi> The ſame voice of Chriſt, that ſent away the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill from himſelfe <hi>(A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid Satan)</hi> will ſend him away from vs alſo, when our temptations (as his) are ended.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our armour is greatly preualent for the foile of this ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. For the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of it, it is called <hi>the armour of God:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.13.</note> and for the compleatneſſe of
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:346:104"/>it, it is called <hi>whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> of God. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this, God will not haue his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraged, as to ſuffer him that vſeth it, to take a repulſe, or ſuffer the armour it ſelfe to be broken and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled.</p>
            <p>The edge of the ſword of the Spirit was neuer yet blunted by the hardineſſe of the enemie: no, <hi>They ouercame him by the word of their teſtimonie, Reu.</hi> 12.11. The Word of God is of an inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:346:105"/>nature: not one tittle of it can paſſe away: it will vphold him that holds it forth, ſo that he cannot pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in his afflictions.</p>
            <p>The ſhield of faith was neuer yet bored or pierced thorow by any darts of the deuill, came they neuer ſo thicke and violent. No: <hi>this is the victorie which ouercommeth the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.4.</note> (both the Prince of it, and the malice, and the allurements, and the affrightments of it) <hi>euen our faith.</hi> Faith, as much as a graine of
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:346:105"/>muſtard ſeed, can doe wonders.</p>
            <p>The <hi>helmet of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was neuer yet beat off the head of Gods Warriour,
<note place="margin">So hope is called, 1 Theſſ. 5.8.</note> by any ſnares of fierie tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which the deuill rained downe vpon him. No: our hope is <hi>a ſure anchor,</hi> ſo <hi>ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt</hi> in apprehending his Obiect, that it <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into that within the veile, Heb.</hi> 6.19.</p>
            <p>By our patience wee may <hi>poſſeſſe our ſoules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 21.19.</note> euen when our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are moſt vrgent vpon vs, and ready to
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:346:106"/>tire vs out. Euen then, when we loue not our liues to the death, wee ſhall ouercome the dragon, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12.11.</p>
            <p>By effectuall and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent praier wee ſhall preuaile much.
<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.</note> The Lord neuer heareth that voice which the Archangell ſpake, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 9.</note> but preſently he conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and ſaith, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee, O Satan, euen the Lord that hath choſen Ieruſalem, rebuke thee, Zech.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>So of all the parts of our Chriſtian armour,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:346:106"/>they are all ſo cutting, and wounding, and deadly in ſlaying, that the enemie (as <hi>Ahab</hi>) muſt die of the blow, and be glad to retire.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the deuill is indeed an enemie, but an enemie already ouercome, and ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with his deaths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wound. Chriſt hath ſpoiled principalities and powers for vs, and triumphed ouer them openly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Croſſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. ſo that all our reſiſtance is (as it were) but the kicking of a curſt beaſt, whoſe
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:346:107"/>throat is already cut; to let out his life-bloud, whereby hee doth yet ſpurn againſt vs. There was no more for the Captaines of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to doe, after the battell ended, but onely to tread vpon the fiue heathen Kings whom <hi>Ioſhua</hi> had ouercome, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Come neere, put your feet vpon the necks of theſe Kings.</hi> The like is the voice of our victorious <hi>Ioſhua:</hi> Come, here are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies foiled to your hands, vp and trample vpon them. Chriſt puls
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:346:107"/>out the ſting of the old helliſh ſerpent, and then ſaith in the words of the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ipſi Chriſto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat Irenaeus, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 38.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt tread vpon the lion and adder; the young lion and the dragon ſhalt thou trample under feet, Pſal.</hi> 91.13. Chriſt put the deuill to his wings, when himſelfe had beene violently tempted: And euer ſince he hath beene ſo crazie and fearfull, that the weakeſt member of Chriſt, vſing the ſame method and meanes of reſiſting, hath beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to chaſe him away.
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:346:108"/>Alſo by vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the ancient Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers who were before Chriſt in time, (being the fore-ward in this barrell) did nor flie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their enemie, but made him to flie, and that euery way as effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caciouſly as wee can doe.</p>
            <p>Fiftly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> our owne weake and fraile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition requireth ſuch reſpite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome times. Sometimes the deuill muſt be gone, that wee may be a little refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reuiued. Wee need a breathing time;
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:346:108"/>and therefore it ſhall not be as the deuill will, who would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes moleſt vs, and get that by importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which by perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he could not get: but, will he, nill he, he muſt ſometimes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. The Lord knows our frame, and how we are but duſt, eaſily foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with long vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: therefore in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he ſtinteth our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, what he ſhall doe, and how long he ſhall ſtay, and when he ſhall auoid; and will
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:346:109"/>not ſuffer vs to be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted aboue that wee are able: An iſſue there is of our trials, and hee will, with the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, make a way to eſcape, that wee may bee able to beare it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>The Lord knowes,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.9.</note> how to deliuer the godly out of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> both when the fit time is, and what are the meanes, and what is the meaſure of his ſeruants ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, hee will haue them haue time, to prepare themſelues for other skirmiſhes:
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:346:109"/>To repaire the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which Satan made, to fortifie their holds where they are weake, to trie their weapons in better manner, to gather their grounds of comfort together, for magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie and vnwearia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe.</p>
            <p>Finally, they ſhall haue ſome ſpace allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy comforts from God, and the ioy of their ſaluation. Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are vncouth, and blacke, and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vex a good
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:346:110"/>heart, and diſquiet the minde with an holy indignation: During which time, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cannot take his portion of reioycing in the Lord, as the word doth allow him. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a time ſhall bee, when this harſhneſſe and bitterneſſe ſhall be gone, and the contrary ſweetneſſe ſucceed in the place.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">Conſolation to the godly.</note>Heare this,
 yee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord, and be comforted. <hi>Reioyce ye heauens, and yee that dwell in them; Now is come ſaluation, and
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:346:110"/>ſtrength, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our God, and the power of his Chriſt: for the accuſer of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren is caſt downe, which accuſed them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our God day and night, Reu.</hi> 12.10.12. The deuill (as malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſubtill as he is, yet) when he is reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, muſt flie away. Hee is of a crauenly brood, and cannot ſtand where he findes a valiant opponent. Let this therefore ſtop all voices of vnquietneſſe, and eſpecially the voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of deſperation,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:346:111"/>whereby the Chriſtian doth many times too much trouble himſelfe. O (ſaith hee) I finde not this doctrine true: the deuill doth not ſo flie from mee, as you ſpeake, but is euer aſſailing mee with thoughts of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, with idle, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and vnlawfull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
<note place="margin">A fourefold anſwer to complaints of Satans te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſneſſe in tempting.</note> I finde almoſt continuall temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. To whom I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, you ſay well, that the deuils tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are <hi>almoſt</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall: for I know they
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:346:111"/>are not continuall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together and wholly. You finde ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing betweene-whiles. And is not this ſome comfort? Doth it not flie away, though it be but for a while? And did he leaue your Lord and Sauiour o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe? It is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that the ſeruant be as his Maſter, and not in better eſtate, <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.25.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, our whole life on earth is a time of warfare, and no part of it can be ſecure from the Tempter. Know
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:346:112"/>therefore, if he ſhould ſtay till death, yet then he muſt be gone. If he flie not at noone, yet he muſt and will flie by night. Only reſiſt, and his backe ſhall be turned vpon you firſt or laſt. Stay the time, and wait when it will be. And take heed you looke not for more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie from trouble, than your preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition will permit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, you ſay the deuill doth not flie from you: Looke and conſider how well you reſiſt him: It may be,
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:346:112"/>you ſhall finde by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, that he ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the longer with you by your owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault. According to our reſiſtance is his flight: and according to our manfulneſſe, his cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardlineſſe. No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if he ſtand his ground where hee is faintly and heartleſly oppoſed. Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our tells vs, that ſome deuils are not caſt out <hi>but by faſting and praier:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 17.21.</note> So alſo, ſome temptations and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtations cannot bee vanquiſhed, but by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:346:113"/>care and ſtriuing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, when the people of God haue their hearts teſtifying with them, that they haue done their beſt in reſiſting the deuill, and yet he flieth not away ſo perfectly as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, let them know this is matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort rather than of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and, if they could remember their grounds, they ſhould rather reioyce than be troubled. So ſaith Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> chap. 1.2. <hi>My brethren, count it all ioy,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:346:113"/>when ye fall into diuers temptations.</hi> For this is a ſigne, that the deuill hath not yet won vs. He is not ſo ſilly and vnwiſe, as to trouble his owne. It is good to haue him our enemie, and we may well bee ioyous in this, euen in the very midſt of all the throng. Woe vnto vs, when the deuill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be our friend. If we be not tried and iudged, as other of Gods people are, wee haue the more cauſe to trie and iudge our ſelues.</p>
            <pb n="200" facs="tcp:346:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="201" facs="tcp:346:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="202" facs="tcp:346:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="203" facs="tcp:346:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="204" facs="tcp:346:116"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">Fond to leaue godlineſſe for a ſuppoſed perpetuitie of moleſtation.</note>Againe, wee ſee by this doctrine, how fond it is to feare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall moleſtation, and ſo leaue the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſound practiſe of godlineſſe. Many thinke, and ſome are not aſhamed to ſay, that if they ſet to ſuch &amp; ſuch exerciſes, they ſhall leade a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholie life euer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: Oh this profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Goſpell, which Miniſters vrge ſo much, is a tedious and vncomfortable profeſſion; they ſhall be ſtill troubled with
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:346:116"/>the deuill, &amp; the world will bee vpon their backs, and manifold vexations they muſt endure. Amongſt the many errors commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the anſwer to the chiefe is this: that there is no enemie they ſhall meet withall in theſe diſtaſted wayes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<note place="margin">No enemie in Chriſtianitie but muſt flie.</note> but if he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, hee muſt flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. It is impoſſible he ſhould ſtand, if we our ſelues be willing to chaſe him away. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Our text is plaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the great and
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:346:117"/>moſt hideous enemie,
whom wee muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter. And as plaine is the Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the other ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Euery one that is borne of God, ouercammeth the world: euen when it commeth againſt vs with tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and diſtreſſe,</hi> and perſecution, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and nakedneſſe, and perill, and ſword: In all theſe things wee are more than conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, through him that loued vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As for our owne fleſh, and the luſts thereof,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:346:117"/>which warre againſt our ſoules, the Lord hath giuen vs his owne Spirit, to take part with vs againſt them: that, as the fleſh luſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> ſo the ſpirit alſo ſhall luſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fleſh, and the body of ſinne ſhall be at laſt deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>As for them that will haue peace without fighting, and hope to paſſe away their liues comfortably, not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelues with the deuill and his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, nor incurring the diſpleaſure of the
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:346:118"/>world, nor yet watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the corruptions of their owne euill hearts; wee enuie them not their peace, but pitie them; hoping, and wiſhing, and deſiring God in our praiers, that he will rowſe them vp out of their fondneſſe, and ſet them forth to know, and meet, and reſiſt, and ouercome their enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label>
               <note place="margin">Be heartie in reſiſting: the euent will giue leaue.</note>Thirdly, let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged hereby, to goe on ſtoutly in reſiſting the deuill; and that in the full meaſure, and
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:346:118"/>due manner, before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. Let them buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle to them the whole armour of God, and ſtill trie it, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did <hi>Sauls,</hi> before he went againſt <hi>Galiah.</hi> Let them repaire breaches, and recouer loſſes, and regaine time, and bee euer watchfull to ſaue themſelues harmleſſe; yea to diſaduantage the enemie, and worke him what diſpleaſure they can: which is, by furthering holineſſe to the vttermoſt, both in themſelues and others. Let them be bold as
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:346:119"/>the righteous are affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be, and goe forth to the fight con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently, aſſuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of a comfortable returne, and ſaying as he to <hi>Goliah, This day will the Lord deliuer thee into mine hand, and I will ſmite thee, and take thine head from thee,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.46. I know the euent will be gladſome, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (by Gods grace) I will reſiſt vnto bloud, to the laſt gaſpe.</p>
            <p>Well, hold that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie is thine, with
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:346:119"/>the ſpoiles, and crowne of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, in as much as the deuill flieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in this life but only for a while, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vſe well the times of reſpite, and of his abſence. Remember he will come againe. <note place="margin">Prouide for Satans return and re-entry.</note>The vncleane ſpirit,
 when hee is gone out of a man, findeth no reſt any where: all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are drie, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable vnto him: and therefore he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth with himſelfe, <hi>I will returne vnto my houſe, from whence I
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:346:120"/>came out, Luk.</hi> 11.24. Though he muſt haue the full foile at laſt, yet he will come and doe miſchiefe as long as he can. And ſome he hath gained by importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Others, whom he could not winne, hee endangered ſhrewdly; put them to much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qoietneſſe; got them to commit great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, eſpecially com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vpon them vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, and ſoone after his departure from them. Wiſdome would therefore, that euery breathing time be well
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:346:120"/>improued, and rather preparation made for a new encounter, than triumphs for the old. Wiſe ſea-men prouide for a ſtorme in a calme: and wiſe Captaines ſtand vpon their guard as well after a battell, as before; fearing, leſt (as the <hi>Amalekites</hi>) they loſe more by their ſecuritie,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 30.20.</note> than they got by their proweſſe and magnanimitie. Let the ſame minde and wiſdome be in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans alſo: ſtill to be in expectation of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and his hoſtilitie,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:346:121"/>and prouide for him accordingly. And let them thinke it enough, that they be at laſt rid of him, neuer to bee again moleſted. When they haue finiſhed their courſe, &amp; fought the good fight of faith, then the crowne ſhall be ſet vpon their heads: out now is their proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label>
               <note place="margin">Follie to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſelues by bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</note>Laſt of all, note here, how falſe it is to ſay the deuill is the cauſe of thy ſinne, and hee muſt beare the blame of it. No: he was not reſifted: if he had, he
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:346:121"/>muſt haue fled away: this promiſe of God is moſt faithſull, and hee that made it, is able to make it good; that (vpon thy reſiſtance, the only neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) it ſhould haue beene performed. Yet this is the ordinary al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation of carnal peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in any groſſe ſin: Oh the deuill owed them a ſpight, and now he hath paid them: the deuill tempted them, and they could not chuſe, and they hope they ſhall not be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:346:122"/>for it. Smaller ſins they ſee not, nor the deuils malice in them: and greater ſinnes they put off wholly to him. So for no ſinnes they betake them to ſerious repentance, neuer ſee any need of Chriſt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer craue mercy at the hands of God as they ought, nor entertaine the due watchfulneſſe, for preuenting the like miſchiefe another time. Such muſt know, that their ſinne cannot be ſo poſted off, but will come home to them againe. That the
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:346:122"/>deuill tempted them, is the deuils ſinne, and he ſhall be damned for it: but, that themſelues conſented, and yeelded to his temptation, is their ſinne, and let them take heed they be not damned for it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. <hi>Eue</hi> ſaid,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent beguiled</hi> her, and ſo he did: but that would not ſerue her turne. Take heed of ſaying and pleading as ſhee did, leſt the like ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table neceſſitie of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment befall thee alſo. Happie is he only, that
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:346:123"/>reſiſteth the deuil: from ſuch an one only, hee ſhall flie away. The Lord make vs all wiſe, and watchfull, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous, to eſpie his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, and oppoſe him in his ſtratagems, that ſo we may be for euer freed from that miſerie and condemnation, which hee and his angels are adiudged vnto.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="219" facs="tcp:346:123"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX of certaine Sermon-Notes vpon</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GEN. 3.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I will put enmitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thee and the woman.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> HOw may I know, whether I haue rightly conceiued, &amp; doe right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manage my enmitie againſt the deuill?</p>
            <pb n="220" facs="tcp:346:124"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Marks of right enmitie againſt the deuill.</note>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> By theſe markes:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, if it be an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of Gods ſetting, namely by the power of his holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſet apart for that purpoſe. So our text ſaith, <hi>I will put enmitie</hi> betweene thee and the woman. Many hate the deuill, but it is only by the force of nature, conceiuing him to be a grim blacke fellow, with hornes, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring eyes, and clouen feet: or according to the common notions they haue receiued
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:346:124"/>from others, from the talke of people, or the like vaine occaſion: Not from the word, for they are ſtrangers to it: nor from the miniſterie of the word, for they deſpiſe it, at leaſt neglect it, and will not be ruled by it.</p>
            <p>Whereas a true Chriſtian conceiueth his hatred of the deuill in the miniſterie, or in a ſerious peruſall of the holy Scriptures. While hee attendeth theſe meanes, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for diſpoſſeſſing the ſtrong man, hee
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:346:125"/>findeth a ſtronger than he ioyning himſelfe to him, and with him; euen the bleſſed Spirit of God,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.4.</note> who is <hi>ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than he that is in the world.</hi> So Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed,
<note place="margin">Luk. 10.18.</note> that he <hi>ſaw Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan fall from heauen like lightning,</hi> to wit, in the Miniſterie of the Diſciples, whom hee ſent, and heard relating their good ſucceſſe. Let this be the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of your enmitie, and if it hold the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it is true: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe counterfet, and only pretended.</p>
            <pb n="223" facs="tcp:346:125"/>
            <p>And this is a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full condition, becauſe God only can main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that enmitie which is neceſſary for vs, and only an enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gods ſetting can preuaile againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Another marke is: If it be for God, for his ſake, for his glory, which was impeached by this enemie, and which we deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer to him againe. True enmitie, as it commeth from God, ſo it goeth to God, and leadeth vs to him;
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:346:126"/>therefore to hate this euill one, becauſe wee wil reuenge our Lords cauſe and quarrell. The moſt hate the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, after their faſhion: but why? only becauſe hee would draw them into hell with himſelfe: and if it were not for thoſe endleſſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſtand vpon hating the deuill. For we ſee, that when they can put thoſe torments out of minde, by iollitie and ſecuritie, they will bee as buſie as Bees, in doing the deuils
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:346:126"/>worke, and caſt off all the faithfull ſeruice of God, it may be, ſcoffe at it, it may be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it. So doe not they that hate him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: They conſider him as one that hath diſhonoured God, and would ſtill diſhonour him, and doth daily in many: and they would haue God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by many, but eſpecially by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: And therefore he that hindreth, ſhall be the obiect of their indignation and dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation. A true naturall
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:346:127"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="223" facs="tcp:346:127"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:346:128"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="225" facs="tcp:346:128"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="226" facs="tcp:346:129"/>ſubiect indeed, goeth to warre for the ſafetie of the King and his kingdome, others for other reſpects: ſo here.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third marke is: If due reſiſtance bee made vpon him, <note place="margin">By vnlawfull things, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue here what things are lawfull.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the counſell, <hi>Reſiſt the deuill, and he will flie from you.</hi> Euery one will reſiſt him whom hee hates, will ſtand againſt him, vſe all poſſible violence, and repell him to his vttermoſt power. So if thou hate the deuill, and take him for thine enemie, thou wilt reſiſt
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:346:129"/>him, and vſe him as an enemie: And it is a ſlim barred, when the parties agree in the maine matter of the contention. Yet ſo doe carnall perſons: They ſay they hate and defie the deuill with all their heart, and yet they yeeld him that, which he mainly ſtriueth for, namely ſinne and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience againſt God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance vpon the deuill.</note>The beginning of this reſiſtance is by vnfained repentance:
 when a man mourneth for his ſinnes, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that hee hath ſo
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:346:130"/>long ſerued the deuill: hee hates and loathes himſelfe in this reſpect, and ſeeth hee had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed for euer, if hee had gone on in the old trade of ſinne. And thoſe who feele not this godly remorſe and ſorrow, neuer yet knew indeed what the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in our Text mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. By nature a man is only what the deuill made him, and of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe he will ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. Therefore hee muſt feele a perfect change, and hate and denie himſelfe; and ſo
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:346:130"/>doing, he begins to vex that helliſh aduerſarie, who is troubled with nothing but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of ſinners, and the companions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with the meanes and effects.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of it.</note>Afterward he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by a carefull and watchfull courſe of life: while a man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueth his workes by mortification, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoureth after full holineſſe, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to keepe off his temptations by the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God. And this wee haue limited
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:346:131"/>by certaine conditions and markes, in the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe on <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by much labour is now ſaued, and this diſcourſe becommeth ſhort which otherwiſe ſhould be large.</p>
            <p>They therefore that ordinarily fall into the ſame ſinnes, and make little conſcience of their waies: They alſo that know in their own hearts, that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin ſecurely; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out watchfulneſſe to the contrary, it is not againſt the purpoſe of their ſoule, they doe it
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:346:131"/>freely, they humble not themſelues for it as an hainous matter, but entertaine it willingly, and hold it peaceably, with eaſe and quietnes of conſcience: All theſe, and all that faile <hi>habitually</hi> in any of the conditions of right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, doe not hate the deuill in truth, but counterfeit an enmity, which at laſt they ſhall ſee was deceiptfull, and ſhall rue the time, that they framed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo childiſh an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt ſo manfull an enemie.</p>
            <pb n="232" facs="tcp:346:132"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly,
if thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the deuill indeed, thou wilt auoide the places of his walke. For ſo doe men with them whom they hate. They will keepe aloofe off, and not willingly come neare thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where ſuch vſe to haunt. The places which the deuill doth moſt vſe vnto, are the <hi>dry places</hi> of the world,
<note place="margin">Luke 11.24.</note> as the Scripture ſpeaks; that is, ſuch as wherein is no moiſture or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment for the ſoule, but ignorance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe raigneth, and
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:346:132"/>a man ſhall rather be hindred than furthered in godlineſſe: As for example, blinde pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes where is no viſion, ale-houſes, play-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſmoke-houſes, and all vngodly meetings: Here the deuill hath a kinde of right, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall power ouer the ſonnes of men; as in that inſtance of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, In meo eam inueni,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de ſpectac. c.</hi> 26. <hi>Eiuſmodi daemoniis pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabiles fiunt.</hi>
               </note> I tooke her vpon my owne ground; ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the deuill to the Exorciſt, which adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and asked him, why he inuaded a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:346:133"/>woman, being at a Play.</p>
            <p>It is true, hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the earth to and fro, comes euen where the immortall ſeed of the word is ſowen, to ſteale it away, and enters into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt cloſets where the heartieſt praiers are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred vnto God: And in none of theſe may wee bee ſecure. But in places of lewd reſort, and in the companion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of euill men, he is ſpecially preſent, as the King and chiefe man, ſpeaking, and ſcoffing,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:346:133"/>and working by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would if hee had fleſh to appeare in. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in the heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this wicked one will either keepe the feet altogether out of ſuch places, which is beſt and ſafeſt; or ſoone carry the feet from them, which is the next point of wiſdome. So doth the bleſſed man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the counſell of the vngodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, nor ſitteth in
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:346:134"/>the ſeat of the ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which maketh ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them that mingle themſelues with ſuch ſociety, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely frequent ſuch places, or liue conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly in ſuch pariſhes. This is amity, not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. Howſoeuer, it is too much familiaritie: and an ill ſigne, that the heart is at too much league with the deuill. A good heart would keepe further off him.</p>
            <p>The fift marke is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> an earneſt begging of ſtrength from God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:346:134"/>the deuill, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a faithfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending vpon him for ſuch ſtrength: as a man wil make all the friends hee can, to diſappoint and annoy one whom he hates: he will call in company, and not truſt his owne only prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and rather get too many on his ſide, than want helpe: ſo heere: A ſpeciall peece of our Chriſtian armour is praier, as the Apoſtle reckoneth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Praying alwaies with all praier and ſupplication in the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. We had
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:346:135"/>need craue wiſdome to eſpie temptations when they come, and grace to repell them, and power to reiect the pleaſures of ſinne, or other wages of vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe whatſoeuer: And that God would maintaine in vs this godly enmitie, and keepe it for euer in the purpoſe of our heart, to hate that enemie; whom otherwiſe, of our ſelues we are ready to loue and ioyne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as a very friend.</p>
            <p>They that are not ſo carefull, are too too
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:346:135"/>careleſſe. Hee can doe little, that cannot call for helpe againſt an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. Yet naturall men thinke themſelues good enough for the deuill. Good hearts, and good faith, and a good deale of ſpetting, ſhall chaſe him quite away. So they forſake the rocke of their health, and forget the ſtrong God of their ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Sixtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> if thou hateſt the deuill aright, then, as neere as thou canſt, thou wilt giue him no aduantage from thy ſelfe. A man that hates
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:346:136"/>another who beares him no good will, but watcheth all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities againſt him, will bee ſure for his owne part to let fall nothing (in word or deede) which may diſaduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage himſelfe, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage that his aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie. So wilt thou watch againſt this ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The deuill doth often get ground of vs through our owne fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as namely, by the paſſions of anger, feare, and the like; by naturall affections, as loue to parents, children, kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:346:136"/>by refections of nature, as about meat, and drinke, and ſleepe, and apparell; by word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſſes, and the diſtractions that attend them; by couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by earthlineſſe, by too much cloſeneſſe and niggardlineſſe: So hee got within <hi>Iudas:</hi> and within <hi>Peter,</hi> by fearefulneſſe: and by choler and furie, he gets within vs not ſeldome, as the Apoſtle ſeemes to argue, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.26, 27. <hi>Be angry, and ſinne not: let not the Sunne goe downe vpon your wrath:
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:346:137"/>Neither giue place to the deuill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which bends main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them that are altogether open and looſe in ſuch things; no watchfulneſſe, no iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie ouer their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull hearts; and ſo giue the deuill as much adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage againſt them, as hee deſireth. And this is of all other the moſt killing miſchiefe, when hee worketh in our troubled affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and deſtroyeth ere we be aware.</p>
            <p>The laſt marke of right enmity is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:346:137"/>endeuour to thruſt downe the Kingdome of the deuill in others: as a man that hates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, will doe him al the miſchiefe he can, hinder his profit, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach his credit and good name, incenſe his friends, and raiſe vp e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies againſt him. Thus the Apoſtles went vp and downe, ſhaking the <hi>ſtrong holds of Satan, and caſting downe euery high thing that exalted it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the knowledge of Chriſt.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. Thus if one who hath
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:346:138"/>authoritie, doth vſe his authoritie for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of diſorders, the ſhaming and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of euill members, the preſeruing of the holineſſe of the Lords Sabbaths: If one that is rich, will be at char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to ſet vp, and hold vp the Ordinances of God, eſpecially the preaching of the word, which giueth the deuill the greateſt blow hee can receiue: If Maſters of families doe chaſe away riotous and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked perſons, and ſet good in the roome, and
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:346:138"/>ſeeke to make all an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly company to the Lord: If priuate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and one neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to another, ſhall vſe admonition in due ſeaſon, call one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from ſinfull cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to the houſe of God, or any other way further the ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſaluation of their brethren: They ſhall doe worthy offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the deuill, and ſhew themſelues to be his right ſworne enemies. Chriſt our Captaine, who ſtrucke at the head of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:346:139"/>was <hi>for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe manifeſted, that he might deſtroy the workes of the deuill,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.8. So alſo doth euery true Chriſtian, who partakes of his anointing: Hee alſo will manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, what hee is, and whoſe he is, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring euery way hee can, to deſtroy the workes of the deuill. And they that are not thus affected, haue not yet the right enmitie in their hearts: they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to hate the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but loue him well enough.</p>
            <pb n="247" facs="tcp:346:139"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>I</label>
               <note place="margin">Three ſorts of men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued.</note>A reproofe it is to diuers.</p>
            <p>If theſe be marks of right enmity, then how many are there, that muſt needs ſay (if they will ſpeake truth) that they neuer yet hated the deuill as they ought? But ſpecially, three ſorts of people come here to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. They that thinke not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this enmitie.</note>Firſt, ſome liuing ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilly and vnblamably among men, are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecure of this hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh enemie, and neuer imagine, that either the deuill practiſeth any
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:346:140"/>thing againſt them, or they ought to watch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. They thinke not at all on ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. They cannot tell, whether there bee any ſuch enmitie or no, or ſhould bee. Yea many take it for their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that they are neuer troubled with thoughts about the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: Oh they are in good caſe, and God hath bleſſed them faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they feele not the afflictions of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which ſuch and ſuch feele, and need not complaine as they doe.
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:346:140"/>And they neuer eſpie the deuil till afterward, that is, when hee hath got them to doe what hee would haue them doe; it may bee, neuer but in the great and groſſe ſinnes of others, Oh the deuill was buſie and great with him that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted murder, that hanged himſelfe, or did ſome notorious wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. But they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer watch before hand, to ſee or preuent him: And they are preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly confident, that they are ſafe, and the deuill ſhall neuer be ſo
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:346:141"/>great with them, as hee was with ſuch &amp; ſuch: That is all their prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that is all their care to keepe him out.</p>
            <p>But as for the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſupplanting of his Kingdome in their brethren, here they are deepely ſecure, and doe nothing at all: neuer care to execute any of thoſe things, in the ſeuenth: The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee the power of Satan in mens hearts and liues: They know what it is, and how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, to bee corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally poſſeſſed of the
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:346:141"/>deuill, and wiſh meanes may bee had to releaſe them; but, what it is to be ſpiritually poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of him, they know not, therefore deſire no meanes for their good. Indeed how ſhould they tender the welfare of others, &amp; haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on the ſoules of others, who neuer knew their owne bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, nor rightly piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their owne ſoules?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. They that embrace the contrary ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>Secondly, ſome are ſo farre from waging enmitie againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, that they haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into moſt neere
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:346:142"/>amitie with him, and giue vp themſelues to be ruled by him at his pleaſure. There ſeemes to be but one head, and one heart, and one hand, and one aime betweene them. Their counſels, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and actions, and intentions are one and the ſame; only for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt God. I meane all prophane perſons, who goe on in a conſtant and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary practiſe of any ſinne, or many ſinnes. If they ſhould doe the deuill a ſpight by daily
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:346:142"/>frequenting of ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, by tipling, by gaming, by ſwearing, or any ſuch abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then they were bitter enemies to him, and they would ſpight him cruelly: for, this they doe day by day, nothing more. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery wiſe man ſeeth, that this pleaſeth the deuill exceedingly, and he is delighted in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his they are, and of them Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>He that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſinne, is of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> They agree with
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:346:143"/>him, as the ſilly Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites with <hi>Abſalom</hi> in his conſpiracie, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. <hi>They went in their ſimplicitie, and knew not any thing.</hi> They are traitors to God ere they be aware, and ſerue Gods grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemie, whom they pretend to hate. None of thoſe vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will yeeld hee is the ſeruant and childe of the deuill, but will ſcorne the motion, and profeſſe the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. But that is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and wee muſt proue ſhortly, that
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:346:143"/>wicked men are <hi>the ſeed</hi> of the helliſh ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Euery one is borne a limbe of the deuill, and hee whom grace altereth not, doth ſo continue, reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling his father in the groſſeſt wickedneſſe; yet ſome more, ſome leſſe, as children are like their parents, ſome more than others.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. They that helpe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, in ſtead of hindring him.</note>Thirdly, ſome there are, who, in ſtead of hating the deuill, and hindring him as they ſhould, doe rather gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie him, and helpe him what they can. I
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:346:144"/>doe not ſay they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to doe him a good turne, and meane abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to ſet him vp for the king and god of the world; but in effect they doe as much: they doe that which doth aduance the deuill and his kingdome among men: Let them bee tried by their <hi>works,</hi> as our Sauiour argued with the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and then, though they ſay neuer ſo often they are the children of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and of God, yet they will be found to be the children of the
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:346:144"/>deuill,
<note place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>for his works they doe:</hi> More; they are indeed his friends, his louing and deare friends, for <hi>his works they ſet forward,</hi> and procure as many as they can, to ioyne with them in the ſame wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: how many are there, who ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to make their brother drunken, and lay him vnder the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? How many, who force oathes vpon their neighbour, and twit a man for a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, who will not rap
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:346:145"/>out a fearfull oath, as they would haue him? How many, that begin miſſe-rule and vile diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders in a place, and that with a ſtrong hand, and a ſtiffe necke, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely to draw others from the obedience of the Miniſterie, &amp; make them like to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in an vnrefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable obſtinacie? and ſo in other inſtances. Woe vnto them: for they lend the deuill their helping hand, and ſtriue againſt true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which hee alſo ſtriueth againſt. This is
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:346:145"/>not enmitie, but amitie in the higheſt degree. Let them looke before hand what the end will be.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">Motiues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the euill ſpirits.</note>And let vs all labour for this enmitie, ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and deſcribed, as wee haue ſeene: Vſing for ſpurres and motiues, theſe enſuing conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, what are thoſe euill ſpirits vnto God? Moſt vile rebels, and deadly enemies: Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at firſt in a moſt blisfull eſtate, with God and his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens:
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:346:146"/>but through pride, or vnbeleefe, or ſome other act of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, they fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and left their firſt habitation; chuſing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to leaue God and his bleſſedneſſe, than their owne opinion conceiued of, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelues. And they are ſtill ſpightfull againſt his Maieſtie, oppoſe his honour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt his counſels and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, obſcure his glory, deface his image on man, and trouble the order of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Now what good
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:346:146"/>ſubiect doth not hate to the death, one that is an arrant traitor, ſtill practiſing againſt his Prince? So ſhould we be affected in this caſe, toward this enemie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, what are the euill ſpirits to vs? As full of malice as they can hold. They tempt vs to euill, and diſſwade vs from good. They ſeeke to corrupt vs in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and moleſt vs in our worſhipping of God. They intercept good means, and what mercies of God they
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:346:147"/>poſſibly can. They accuſe vs, and raiſe vp ſlanderers, perſecutors, other enemies; with ſtormes, and tempeſts, and witches, and other miſchiefes, to diſturbe and fret vs, and worke vs to impatience, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie, atheiſme; as he ſaid of <hi>Iob,
<note place="margin">Iob 1.11.</note> Touch him now, and hee will blaſpheme thee to thy face;</hi> and ſo he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his owne wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe againſt him, vſing alſo his wife to that purpoſe,
<note place="margin">chap. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Doeſt thou yet retaine thine innocencie? blaſpheme
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:346:147"/>God and die.</hi> And there is no poſſibilitie hee ſhould be better affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to vs: therefore hate him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, what are thoſe ſpirits in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? Euill, onely euill, continually euill, greedie to doe euill, watchfull thereunto, and gaping after euery opportunitie to further it. They loue neither God nor man, no not them that are one with them and obey them in all things. They loue nothing properly, but ſinne and miſchiefe.
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:346:148"/>This they intend prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, fully, willingly, maliciouſly. Therefore alſo all their ſinnes are ſinnes againſt the holy Ghoſt; therefore can neuer bee pardoned, neither in this life, nor the life to come. They are reprobates, held in the chaines of blacke darkneſſe againſt the iudgement of the great day. Briefly, there cannot be the like ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect for our hatred, in all the world: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hate them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, GOD, whom we muſt <hi>follow
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:346:148"/>as deare children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.1.</note> doth hate them vnreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably. He hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no Redeemer, nor Mediator for them; hath made no promiſe of life to them, nor co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of mercy, nor giuen them the leaſt hold of him, whereby they might be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: But contrarily, he hath written in the Scripture the ſentence of their condemnation, hath nominated his children to bee their Iudges, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.3. and hath appointed them in the meane
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:346:149"/>time to exerciſe all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilitie againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, both here; and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Giue no place to the deuill:</hi> and <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Reſiſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,</hi> and hee will flie from you, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. Then follow your Captaine. Doe as yee ſee mee doe, ſaid <hi>Gideon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, the faithfull ſeruants of God haue ſtill held vp this oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition againſt him; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Angels of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael,</hi> who fought with the dragon, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him. Yea they
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:346:149"/>reioyced, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils were ſubdued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.17. ſee <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. And though good men haue ſometimes beene ſore ſhaken, and foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, yet they haue got ground againe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered their loſſes, and done him the more hurt for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe againſt them; ſhaking his kingdome the more manfully. Then ioyne with theſe armies of the Lord, and march on with them. And know, that none is on their ſide,
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:346:150"/>but ſuch as are againſt God; none but carnall and worldly men, none but the ſeed of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, the children of the deuill; none but they whoſe example muſt be odious to vs as hell it ſelfe. Count that fight good, which good men maintaine, and euill men traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly let alone, or ioyne with the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, the hatred of the deuill is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, if not the ground of true grace. God is not loued, nor
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:346:150"/>feared, nor ſerued, nor any way truly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, till this enmitie againſt the deuill bee wrought in the heart. Thus the termes of our conuerſion are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. <hi>To turne them from darkneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan vnto God.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Yee cannot ſerue God and Mammon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 6.24.</note> and, <hi>The one muſt be hated, that the other may be embraced;</hi> ſo ſay I, that the deuill muſt be hated if God muſt be
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:346:151"/>loued, wee cannot loue or ſerue both together. Well a man may play on both ſides, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding loue to God while hee doth what the deuill would haue him doe, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an hatred of the deuill while he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth the will and worke of God: But indeed and in truth he cannot loue God, till the deuill be truly and vnfainedly hated. And, where is no true loue of God, there is no true faith, nor hope, nor patience, nor hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:346:151"/>nor any ſound grace whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Adde hereunto theſe meditations. We hate leſſer enemies, and for ſmaller occaſions, and why not this, for the greateſt occaſion that can be? He ſpoiled vs of the grace of creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and, if hee could, would ſpoile vs of the grace of regeneration alſo. He caſt vs downe from our happie eſtate, wherein wee were firſt placed, and would caſt vs downe from that happineſſe, which Chriſt hath recouered
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:346:152"/>for vs, with the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of his owne bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Beſide, this enmitie is the beginning of our returne to God, and of our reconciliation with him; as here to our firſt parents. God loues not vs, till wee hate the deuill, and that vnfainedly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> And finally, we muſt know, that if wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues with a falſe hatred in ſtead of a true, the time ſhall come, when wee ſhall hate the deuill whether we will or no; and hate
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:346:152"/>our ſelues, who would be ſo ſillily deluded, and ſhall for euer curſe both: for he and his angels are caſt out, and their place is found no more in heauen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:346:153"/>
            <pb n="275" facs="tcp:346:153"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>CYPRIAN in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Arum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> It is a ſmall matter, that wee ſtirre vp the people of GOD
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:346:154"/>with the Trumpet of our voice, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe alſo, by leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons taken out of Gods Word, wee ſtrengthen the faith of Beleeuers, and their vertue which is dedicated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted vnto GOD. And what doth more ſuit with our (Paſtorall) care, than that, by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall exhortations, wee fence the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:346:154"/>commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vs of God, and the Armie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in the heauenly camp, againſt the batterie and darts of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill? For a ſouldier cannot bee fit for warre, if he be not firſt trained in the field; And hee that would get the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land by wreſtling, yet ſhall not bee crowned, if he doe
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:346:155"/>not firſt practiſe, and trie his skill, and ſtrength. It is an old Aduerſarie, and an ancient E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, with whom wee muſt combat. Six thouſand yeers are almoſt finiſhed,
<note place="margin">This he wrote about the yeere of the world 5457. <hi>Euſeb. Auguſt. Oroſ. Sulpit. Scuerus.</hi> But there ſeemes to be an error</note> ſince the deuill did ſet vpon mankind. So that now, by his long ſtanding, and great experience, he hath learned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly all ſorts of
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:346:155"/>temptations, and all the feats and ſnares of deſtroying. If hee ouertake the ſouldier of Chriſt vnprepared, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, or not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and watchfull with his whole minde, he circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents him vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, and deceiues him in his ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But if a man keepe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:346:156"/>God, and ſtoutly cleaue to the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of Chriſt, and then ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand &amp; reſiſt him, he muſt needs bee ouercome; becauſe Chriſt whom wee profeſſe, is inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible.</p>
            <p>See heere (Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader) the conſent of this ancient Father, and glorious Martyr of Chriſt, to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer doctrine. If thou receiueſt the teſtimony
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:346:156"/>of man; know the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But bee ſure by all theſe admonitions, to buckle on thy harneſſe, &amp; looke for this grand enemie, and reſiſt him. Leaue this intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſo much with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of State, and pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aduerſaries, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this principall principally. For, what will it auaile thee, to be free from men, and in bondage to the deuill? what good, to Lord it in earth, and be guilty of hell fire? to conſpire with thine owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:346:157"/>heart, abuſed by the deuill (where the end will bee death eternall) and diſcouer the treacheries of men, to their vtter diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace? Will this quit coſt? Call therefore thy thoughts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> homeward. Looke to thine owne houſe,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.20.</note> and bleſſe it. Marke the poſſeſſions and ſtrong holds of the ſtrong man, and caſt him out. If he deceiue thee, how great is that deceit? Thrice vnhappy is that man, and more, who
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:346:157"/>liues too well knowne to others, and dies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to himſelfe. It had beene good for that man, if he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene borne.</p>
            <p>One alarme more, and ſo I lay aſide my Trumpet. Reſiſt the deuill, reſiſt, reſiſt: not ſcorne, but reſiſt: and reſiſt him in all wicked motions whatſoeuer: reſiſt him by the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons appointed, the armour of God; reſiſt him early, ſtoutly, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally, wiſely, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly: Bee carefull herein, and iealous, that
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:346:158"/>thou reſiſteſt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: And remember that thou haſt not yet reſiſted vnto bloud, ſtriuing againſt ſin; and prouide ſo to doe. The Lord giue thee a heart and courage hereunto, and afterward ſet the crowne of victory on thy head. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:346:158"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
